<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse the 4 of December, 1597 wherein is discoursed that all buying and selling of spirituall promotion is vnlawfull / by Iohn Howson ...</title>
            <author>Howson, John, 1557?-1632.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03763</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13882</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2747</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24582832</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24582832</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27798</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03763)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27798)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1854:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse the 4 of December, 1597 wherein is discoursed that all buying and selling of spirituall promotion is vnlawfull / by Iohn Howson ...</title>
                  <author>Howson, John, 1557?-1632.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Th. Adams,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1597.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in paging.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XXI, 12-13 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Simony --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27798:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27798:1"/>
            <p>A Sermon preached at Paules Croſſe the 4. <hi>of December.</hi> 1597.</p>
            <p>Wherein is diſcourſed, <hi>that all buying and ſelling of Spirituall promotion is vnlawfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By IOHN HOVVSON, Student of <hi>Chriſtes</hi>-Church in Oxeford.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed for <hi>Th. Adams.</hi> 1597.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:27798:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27798:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>A Sermon preached at Paules Croſſe the 24. of <hi>December</hi> 1597. by <hi>Iohn Howſon,</hi> Student of <hi>Chriſts-Church</hi> in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The text.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>And Ieſus went into the Temple of God, and eaſt out all them that ſold and bought in the Temple &amp; ouerthrew the Tables of the money-changers, and the ſeates of them that ſold doues:</p>
                  <p>And ſaid to them; it is written, mine houſe ſhall be called the houſe of prayer: but yea haue made it a denne of theeues.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Mat. 21.12. &amp; 13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is affirmed by them that haue beſt laboured, and euen ſpent their ſpirites to diſcouer the profound myſteries of the holy ſcriptures, that the text <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>textus,</hi> the <hi>webbe</hi> of it, is ſo cunningly and ſo skilfully wouen by the holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, that it is, <hi>omnibus acceſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> but <hi>pauciſſimis penetrabilis;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Epiſt. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> that is to be handled &amp; felt of any man, but few eies can pierce to the ground-worke of it. Which truth wrought this confeſſion in <hi>Chryſologus</hi> an ancient learned and deuout Writer, ſo called for the golden ſentences which proceeded from him, that <hi>Singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la ſcripturae verba, ſi libris ſingulis mandarentur, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Serm.</hi> 64.</note> which is, If there were a booke written, a particular booke of euery particular word almoſt, in the holy Scriptures; yet the miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris of them could not by that meanes bee ſufficiently diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to vs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:27798:3"/>Wherefore (right Honourable, &amp;c.) it is not to bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected at my handes, that in this ſhort time, limited to the meaſure of my ſtrength and your patience, I ſhould deliuer vnto you whatſoeuer is noteable or noted alreadie by ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reuerend and learned Fathers (old and new) of the litte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, hiſtoricall, morall, or allegoricall ſenſe of this ſcripture; nor to make application according to the variety and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of ſenſe, which the ſpirit of God hath imparted to you, moſt reuerend Fathers and learned Diuines: for I doe not preſume to ſpeake that <hi>quod potiſſimum dicendum eſſet;</hi> which is indeed moſt fitte to bee ſpoken; ſeeing it is a great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and aboue the common and ordinary reach, <hi>nihil dicere quod dicendum non eſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hug in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſt. Hom. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> to ſay nothing which were not better vnſaid, than ſpoken.</p>
            <p>Wherfore as Saint <hi>Luke</hi> diuided his firſt Sermon, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 1. his Ghoſpell, which comprehended the whole life of our Sauiour Chriſt, into two partes, into thoſe things, <hi>quae coepit Ieſus Facere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 1.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; Docere;</hi> which hee did, and which hee taught, into his Dooings, and into his Sayings: ſo doo I diuide this Text, <hi>in Factum, &amp; Dictum;</hi> into a Deed of his, and into a Speech of his; into an Action of his, and the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it. The Action in theſe wordes, <hi>And Ieſus went into the Temple of God, and cast out all them that ſold and bought in the Temple, &amp;c.</hi> The Reaſon; <hi>And ſaid vnto them it is written, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Action.</note>The Action was a reformation of certaine abuſes or prophanations of the Temple of God: In which I obſerue theſe circumſtances. Firſt the Author, <hi>vvho;</hi> ſecondly the Time, <hi>vvhen;</hi> thirdly the Place, <hi>vvhere;</hi> fourthly the Matter, <hi>vvhat;</hi> and fiftly the Manner, <hi>how</hi> this reformation was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. The author.</note>For the firſt, the Author of this reformation is our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt Ieſus, who performed it not as a man onely, or the true ſonne of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> or the ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſonne of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> not as hee was <hi>factus ſub lege,</hi> Galath. 4. <hi>made vnder the law;</hi> nor to ſuffer <hi>in the fleſh;</hi> 1. Pet. 4. nor to bee <hi>crucified concerning his infirmitie</hi> 2. Cor. 13. but as the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:27798:3"/>
onely begotten of God, <hi>the chiefe Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>the King of Kinges, whoſe dominion is from ſea to ſea, and from the riuer to the endes of the land.</hi> Pſal. 72. whoſe office and authority, that is his Kingdome and Prieſthood was prefigured by the two crownes, the ſiluer and the golden crowne, which were hung vp in the Temple. <hi>Zach.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>Now in this Author of this reformation,<note place="margin">Two thinges required in a reformer.</note> I obſerue for this preſent, two things, which are required in al good reformers. One is his authority, that hee is a King and a Prieſt: the other his conditions and qualities, that hee is without fault him-ſelfe that reformeth other. Without the firſt, that is au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, there can bee no reformation; without the ſecond, hardly any good reformation.</p>
            <p>That it was performed by our Sauiour who was King and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Prieſt, it argueth how conuenient the counſell and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Prieſt is, for the ciuill magiſtrate in reforming the Temple: for as the Prieſt may attempt nothing, no al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration without the prince (and therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> when hee came to <hi>Athens,</hi> though hee ſaw Idols and Altars,<note place="margin">Act. 27.</note> and one <hi>ignoto Deo,</hi> to the vnkowne GOD yet hee offered no violence, but preached vnto them the <hi>GOD which they knew not;</hi> and though hee ſaw Idols and Idolatry in the Temple of <hi>Diana,</hi> yet hee offered no violence;<note place="margin">Acts. 19.</note> but preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only, <hi>they were not Gods that were made with handes;</hi> and pulled not downe the ſigne of <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux</hi> in the ſhippe of <hi>Alexandria</hi> that carryed him to <hi>Rome:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 28.</note>) ſo it is conuenient that the Princes and ciuill Magiſtrates in their reformations of the Church and Religion take counſaile and aduiſe of the Prieſtes and the Prophets: and therefore King <hi>Dauid</hi> when he would haue built the Temple,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 7.</note> hee ſent for the Prophet <hi>Nathan,</hi> and tooke counſaile of him.<note place="margin">4. Reg. 12.</note> And <hi>Ioas</hi> did nothing amiſſe in the preſence of God, ſo long as he was informed by <hi>Iehoiada</hi> the Prieſt. And <hi>Ezechias</hi> did the thing that pleaſed the Lord, and remained ſtedfaſtly in the waies of <hi>Dauid</hi> his father,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 48.</note> while <hi>Eſay</hi> the great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and faithfull in his viſion, commanded him. And God ſtirred vp the ſpirit of <hi>Zorobabel,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Iudah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Agg. 2.</note>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:27798:4"/>
and the ſpirit of <hi>Iehoſua</hi> the high Prieſt, that they ioyntly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether might reſtore the building of the Temple; all which argue, that the wiſdome and knowledge of the Prieſt is to be ioyned with the authoritie of the Prince in eſtabliſhing or reforming the Church of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Heb, 7. 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et, 2. 2 Cor, 5. 1 Ioh, 3. 8. Iohn.</note>Secondly, that it was performed by our Sauiour Chriſt, who was <hi>holy, harmeleſſe &amp; vndefiled; who did noe ſin,</hi> as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>who knew no ſinne,</hi> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith; who <hi>hadde no ſinne in him,</hi> as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith; and therefore might ſafely ſay, <hi>which of you can rebuke me of ſinne?</hi> It argueth that they which are reformers of Churches, yea and of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, ſhould be <hi>holy, harmeleſſe, vndefiled, and vncorrupt,</hi> as much as may bee, leaſt vnder the colour of reformation they bring in a deformation, and where they bee choſen to bee <hi>Rephaims,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut, 2.</note> that is, Phiſitions or reformers of vices, they become <hi>Zanzumins</hi> corrupters, wicked and abhominable. For although <hi>ex malis moribus bonae leges cauſaliter,</hi> Euill manners are the occaſion of making good lawes: Yet wicked men are ſeldome the authors of good lawes: but <hi>Valerius Flaccus turpiſſimus author erit turpiſſimae legis. Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerius Flaccus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vell. Patere.</note> a wicked and corrupt man, will bee the author (as farre forth as hee may) of a wicked and corrupt law: or if not of a wicked law, yet of a cunning law, with a faire gloſſe and pretence of the common wealth, when hee is indeede <hi>intentus ſibi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pachimer.</note> attentiue onely to his owne profite and priuate gaine; with a faire gloſſe and pretence of the ſafety of the ſtate, when hee ſeeketh to ſatisfie his owne malice, or effect ſome reuenge; as the Prieſtes and Phariſies made a law to put our Sauiour Chriſt to death, leaſte <hi>the</hi> Romains <hi>ſhoulde come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh, 11.</note> 
               <hi>and take away both their place and their nation;</hi> with a faire gloſſe and pretence to maintaine the priuiledges of the people, or the authority of the Senate, as amongſt the <hi>Romaines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sal. in Cat.</note> when <hi>pro ſua quiſque potentia certabat,</hi> euery man endeuoured to aduance and increaſe his owne honour with a faire gloſſe and pretence to relieue the poore, when; <hi>ex ipſo remedio morbi naſcuntur,</hi> pouerty is increaſed in ſome other eſtate.<note place="margin">Plin. l. <hi>2.</hi> op. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> Theſe and a number the like, are the iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:27798:4"/>
and effects, when wicked and corrupt men do aſpire to the place and authority <hi>emendandi, id est, diſperdendi,</hi> as <hi>Pliny</hi> ſaith, of <hi>reforming that is deforming a ſtate:</hi> whereas if they bee holy, and iuſt, and incorrupt, as our Sauiour Chriſt was, I ſay not in eſſence, but in imitation:<note place="margin">Scueriſſimar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i ſed iuſtiſſima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum legum author.</note> nay but as iuſt as <hi>Lycurgus</hi> the heathen was, who was the maker of moſt ſeuere, but moſt iuſt lawes, the reformation would bee iuſt though ſomewhat ſeuere, as was this reformation of our Sauiour Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For the Time if we conſider it, in reſpect of our Sauiour Chriſt, as in what time of his life it was done,<note place="margin">2. Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. The Time. 4. Reg. 12. 4. Reg. 23.</note> as wee conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and obſerue in what yeare of a Princes reigne he begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his reformation; as it is ſaid, in the 23. yeare of <hi>Ioas</hi> reigne hee repaired the Temple; and <hi>Ioſias</hi> in his 18. yeare reformed religion: may it pleaſe you to vnderſtand that it was done towards the end of his life, when hee was euen now going to his paſſion. And leaſt you ſhould gather hereby, that the reformation of religion, or of the Church, or abuſes thereof, ſhould bee the laſt thing which a good Prince or Magiſtrate ſhould regarde, when <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> could ſay; that with euerie good Magiſtrate, in euery good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the firſt and the chiefeſt thing is, the regard of eſtabliſhing or reforming of religion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Polit. l.</hi> 7 <hi>cap.</hi> 8</note> 
               <hi>and the Church of God:</hi> you ſhall vnderſtand, that with the like action he began his office, as it appeareth in Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Goſpell, where alſo with a whip of little cordes, preſently after his firſt miracle, at his firſt comming to the Temple,<note place="margin">Iohn. 2.</note> hee caſt out the ſheepe, and the oxen, and the ſellers of them: So that if <hi>Omnis Chriſti actio</hi> be <hi>nostra inſtructio,</hi> euery acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Sauiour Chriſt bee a leſſon for vs, wee may learne by this that it is not onely the laſt office, which a good Prince or Magiſtrate ſhould put in practiſe, to reforme the abuſes in the Church of God, but the firſt alſo; and not onely the firſt, but alſo the laſt, the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> and not the firſt and the laſt, but his continuall endeuour. And therefore where all ancient Writers agree that this was put in practiſe twice by our Sauiour; ſome learned men of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:27798:5"/>
later time ſay,<note place="margin">Aret. ſuper. <hi>21.</hi> Matth.</note> 
               <hi>Ter hoc fecit Chriſtus,</hi> Chriſt did it thrice. Firſt in the beginning of his preaching; <hi>Iohn</hi> 2. Secondly, <hi>in die palmarum,</hi> that is in this place; and thirdly when hee returned out of <hi>Bethania,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 11.</note> and curſed the Fig-tree. So that if it bee demanded what is the firſt dutie or vertue of a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate; wee may anſwere out of this example; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the abuſes and prophanations in the Church of God? And if wee demaund what the ſecond dutie or ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of a Magiſtrate is? wee may anſwer out of this place; to reforme the abuſes and prophanation of the Church of God? and if we demaund what is the third dutie or vertue of a Magiſtrate; wee may anſwere; To reforme, &amp;c? Not that the Common-wealth or ciuill affaires ſhould be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected but becauſe if the ſubiects doe,<note place="margin">1. Pet 2.</note> 
               <hi>Deum timere,</hi> Feare God, that will follow naturally which lyeth orderly in the text, they will <hi>Regem honorificare,</hi> Honour their King: if they feare God,<note place="margin">Xenoph. in Cyropaep. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> they will honor their King: and as <hi>Cyrus</hi> could ſay very well, if all the ſubiects were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God, they would giue the King his honor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If wee conſider the time in reſpect of the ſeaſon of the yeare, or according to the diuiſion of dayes, which the wiſe man maketh, where ſome dayes are ſayd to bee <hi>choſen and ſanctified,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 33.</note> as the holy-dayes and ſolemne feaſts; and ſome to be <hi>numbred</hi> onely, as the firſt or ſecond of ſuch a month: both this reformation and the former <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2. was, <hi>in festo Paſchatis,</hi> when hee came to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to celebrate the feaſt of the Paſſeouer.<note place="margin">Deut. 16.</note> For at three feaſts in the yeare, all the males were bound by the lawe to appeare before God in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> in the feaſts of <hi>Easter, Pentecost,</hi> and the <hi>Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lyra ſuper. <hi>2.</hi> cap. Iohn.</note> And although as <hi>Lyra</hi> noteth in two feaſts of <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecost</hi> and the <hi>Tabernacles,</hi> thoſe that dwelt farre off were ſometimes diſpenſed with; yet there was no diſpenſation for the feaſt of <hi>Eaſter.</hi> Now our Sauiour Chriſt vntill his Paſſion did obſerue the lawe duly, and conſequently at theſe feaſts did aſcend to <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now it is probable that to the imitation of this, it was prouided in former and ancient times of Chriſtianitie, as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:27798:5"/>
appeareth <hi>in Concilio Agathenſi Can.</hi> 18.<note place="margin">Concil. Agathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ſub. Xiſto. <hi>3.</hi> circa. anu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>440.</hi>
               </note> That all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians of lawfull age ſhould ioyntly together at their pariſh Churches receiue the Sacrament of the Lords ſupper, at three ſpeciall feaſts in the yeare, at the feaſt of the <hi>Natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Eaſter,</hi> and <hi>Pentecoſt:</hi> and although a diſpenſation were admitted ſometimes at two of theſe feaſts, yet at <hi>Eaſter</hi> (no remedie) all ſhould receiue. Which kinde of imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſome ceremonies of the old law, obſerued by anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, I cannot condemne: For although <hi>old thinges are paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed away,</hi> yet behold new thinges are come in their place.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.</note> And although all things are not to be made and ordered, as <hi>Moyſes</hi> was commaunded to make the Tabernacle,<note place="margin">Heb. 8.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>according to the example or patterne that was ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him in the mount;</hi> that is according to the example of the old law: (for we refuſe the carnall obſeruations of the law, and ſuch types and figures as repreſent our Sauiours comming in the fleſh, or thoſe benefits and bleſſings which were proper and peculiar vnto the Iewes) yet as the Iewes had a King, though their kingdome be now aboliſhed; ſo we haue a new King, <hi>Vbi eſt qui natus eſt rex Iudaeorum?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 2.</note> a King which is borne both to Iewes and Gentiles. And as they haue an old Teſtament, ſo wee haue a <hi>new Teſtament:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.</note> and as they had the ſpirit, ſo we haue a <hi>new Spirit; I will giue vnto you a new heart and a new Spirit:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 36.</note> and as they had Commaundements, ſo wee haue a <hi>new Commaundement; A new Commaundement Giue I vnto you:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 13.</note> and as they had an inheritance promiſed them, the land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> ſo wee haue a new inheritance promiſed vs;<note place="margin">Apoc. 21.</note> 
               <hi>I ſaw a new hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and a new earth:</hi> and as they had their Temple, ſo we haue our Churches: and as they had their Sacraments, ſo we haue our Sacraments: and as they had their Sabboth, ſo wee haue our Sunday: And as they had their Feaſtes, ſo wee haue our Feaſtes and new Holydaies, to put vs in minde of thoſe bleſſings we haue receiued of the bounty of God: one feaſt to remember his Natiuity, another to put vs in minde of his Paſſion, another of his Reſurrection, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other of his Aſcention, another of other ſpirituall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinges,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:27798:6"/>
either performed to vs by our Sauiour Chriſt or his bleſſed Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>And no doubt if ſome ceremonies were neceſſary to bee obſerued among Gods people to retaine the memory of bleſſinges receiued, and maintaine the hope and expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Meſſias to come, ſeeing wee that are Chriſtians are as vnthankfull and forgetfull of the manifold bleſſings of God as they were, &amp; it is as hard a matter &amp; as miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to vs, to beleeue that which is paſt 1600. yeres ſince, as for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to beleeue that which was to come, ſeeing neither they, nor wee, are eye-witneſſes of it, but giue credit to other; they to their Prophets whom in things to come they firmely beleeued; we to our Euangeliſts &amp; Apoſtles whome we cannot deny, or ſuſpect in things that are paſt; wee haue as good vſe of our rites and ceremonies as they had of theirs. I giue this breefe note the rather becauſe as S. <hi>Baſil</hi> complained of his time,<note place="margin">Baſil. ep <hi>70.</hi>
               </note> it is reckoned a great fault and euen ſuperſtition amongſt vs. <hi>Si quis paternas traditiones di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligenter obſeruet,</hi> if a man obſerue dilligently the rites and ceremonies comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nded by the Church and receiued from all antiquity.</p>
            <p>And yet heere wee finde that our Sauiour Chriſt according to the ancient cuſtome of the Iewes goeth vp yearely to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to celebrate the Paſſeouer, and ſatisfie the lawe and the ceremonies of the lawe, that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched not to him: and ſuffered him-ſelfe to bee circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, which needed not euen by the reaſon of the lawe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was <hi>intacta matre natus;</hi> and his mother fulfilled the ceremony of purification, which was not neceſſary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe was not comprehended vnder the lawe, for <hi>non ſuſcepto ſemine conceperat;</hi> ſhee conceiued not as other wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men did,<note place="margin">Luke, 1.</note> but was ouerſhadowed by the holy Ghoſt: and he was ſubiect to his parents, which was not <hi>ſubiectio neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lyra.</note> but <hi>pietatis,</hi> not matter of neceſſity, but rather exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of piety and obedience: and here we find him not onely obſeruing the ſabboth, but other ſollemne feaſts, to teach vs,<note place="margin">Super. Ioh. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> ſaith <hi>Marlorat,</hi> to come to Church on holidaies, as well
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:27798:6"/>
as on Sundaies. A great negligence or rather contempt by little and little crept in amongſt vs, I meane not them that are irreligious, and little regard any ſeruice of GOD, but euen of ſuch who haue euen in their mouthes, though not <hi>templum Domini</hi> the temple of the Lord (for they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard not the place,) yet <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abbatum Domini,</hi> the Lords Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both; but thinke no day holy, or lawfull to be deuoted to the ſeruice of God, but the ſeauenth day onely.</p>
            <p>But as the Iewes beeing too much affected to the letter of the law, or miſled by the Phariſies the interpreters of it, thought the fift Commaundement to be violated onely by murther and ſlaughter of a man, and the 6, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement broken onely by actuall adultery; but our Sauiour playing the interpreter, telleth them, <hi>Verely, verely I ſay vnto you, that hee that is vnaduiſedly angry doth murther,</hi> and <hi>hee that looketh after a woman to luſt after her doth commit adultery,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> though there be difference in the ſins: ſo we ſay vnto you who thinke the violating of the ſeauenth day, to bee onely againſt the fourth commandement, we ſay that the breach and prophanation not only of the greater ſollemnities, <hi>viz. Chriſtmas, Eaſter, Whitſontide,</hi> &amp;c. are the breach of the Sabboth, but alſo the prophanation of the ſmaller feaſtes, which are appointed for the ſeruice of God, and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of thoſe bleſſings we haue receiued by the meanes of his ſeruants, is the breach of the Sabboth. And therefore in the holy Scriptures we finde, not only the ſeauenth day called the Sabboth, but al other feaſts &amp; holy daies, either appointed by God, or the lawfull Magiſtrate, as in the 23. of <hi>Leuit.</hi> where the firſt day of the ſeuenth moneth,<note place="margin">Leuit. 13.</note> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other feaſts are called the Sabboth: And leaſt you ſhoulde thinke that theſe feaſtes had the name onely of a Sabboth, and not the ſollemnization; you may reade that <hi>Heſter</hi> &amp; <hi>Mardocheus</hi> in remembrance of the deliuerance of the Iewes, proclaimed a feaſt or holydaie to be obſerued yearely, and added this law, <hi>Nulli liceat hos duos dies abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſolemnitate tranſigere:</hi> that it ſhould be lawfull for no man to paſſe ouer thoſe daies, but in great ſollemnity; and the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:27798:7"/>
new feaſt inſtituted by <hi>Iudas Machabaeus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eneauia.</hi> Ioh. 10.</note> our Sauiour ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, as wee read in the Goſpell; and walked not in the ſtreetes, but came <hi>In porticum Solomonis,</hi> into the houſe of God, into that place where in all probability, hee did vſe to teach, when it is ſaid he came into the Temple: and thus far by occaſion of the ſecond circumſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The third cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance.</hi> Chryſoſt in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re imperfecto.</note>The third circumſtance is the place where he began this reformation; and that was in the Temple of God, <hi>and Ieſus went into the Temple of GOD. S. Chriſoſotome, in opere im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfecto,</hi> or the author whoſoeuer, noteth it to bee the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of a good ſonne, firſt to viſit his fathers houſe when hee commeth to towne, and performe that duety and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which is due vnto him: And here wee ſee, our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt when he commeth to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> firſt to viſit his fathers houſe <hi>Templum Dei,</hi> the Temple of God, though now for the abuſe thereof it might bee called <hi>Templum Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeorum,</hi> the Temple of the Iewes, as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> calleth the feaſt of the Paſſouer,<note place="margin">Ioh 2.</note> 
               <hi>Paſcha Iudaeorum,</hi> not <hi>Paſcha Dei,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Iewes abuſed it by their inuentions, as Saint <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> noteth vpon that place;<note place="margin">Origen. Ibid.</note> but conſidering the firſt inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he calleth it the <hi>Temple of God,</hi> though by abuſe it was become <hi>a den of theeues.</hi> And wherein ſhould a good ſonne rather buſie himſelfe, than in reforming the abuſes of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe, the gouernment whereof is committed to him, as our Sauiour tolde <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and his bleſſed mother;<note place="margin">Luke, 2.</note> 
               <hi>muſt I not goe about my fathers buſineſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now although the people were called the people of GOD; and the Cittie, the Cittie of God, as wee read euery where in the Pſalmes and Prophets, though as it is in the propheſie of <hi>Eſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay, 1.</note> 
               <hi>The faithfull Cittie was become an harlot,</hi> and <hi>had neither Iudgement, nor Iuſtice in it,</hi> and the people of God become, <hi>a ſinful nation,</hi> and <hi>a people laden with iniquity;</hi> yet he beginneth not his reformation there, but in the <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Giuing this as a leſſon by his example to all Princes, and Magiſtrates to whome it may appertaine, that as a Phiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on when hee comes vnto a ſicke man, firſt demaundeth the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:27798:7"/>
ſtate of his ſtomacke, and laboureth eſpecially to order it, (becauſe if the ſtomacke bee ſounde, the body is ſtrong, if the ſtomacke be ſicke, the whole body is weakned;) ſo the Magiſtrate when hee findeth the bodie of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth diſeaſed, or diſtempered, let him firſt inquyre after the ſtomacke how that is affected, that is, what is amiſſe in Church and Church-men; for from thence as from the roote, or from the heart, or from the fountaine, or from the ſtomacke, proceedeth the health, or the diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the ſinnes or the vertues, of the Prince and the people:<note place="margin">Chriſost. in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re imperfecto.</note> as S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> obſerueth, <hi>De templo omne bonum egredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, de templo omne malum procedit,</hi> From the Temple com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth all good, and from the Temple proceedeth all euill: For the vertues of the Prieſt are like the oyntment, <hi>which being powred vpon</hi> Aarons <hi>head runneth downe to his beard and ſo along to the border and ſkirts of his garment,</hi> that is, firſt affect the Magiſtrate, &amp; them that are ſeated in higher places, and ſo by degrees the meaneſt people: and the ſinne of the Clergie is like a rheume, which aſcendeth out of the ſtomacke into the head, and from thence ſpreadeth it ſelfe, into all parts of the body: according to that of <hi>Leuiticus, Si ſacerdos qui vnctus eſt peccauerit, faciet delinquere populu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leuit. 4.</note> If the Prieſt which is the annointed of the Lord, ſhall hap to ſin, he ſhal cauſe the people to ſin alſo. So that if the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be good and vertuous, the Prieſt may ſay as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Corinth. Nonne opus meum vos eſtis in Domino?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.</note> are not you my workemanſhip in the Lord? If the people be ill, they may ſay to the Prieſt,<note place="margin">Hug. Card.</note> 
               <hi>Nonne deſtructio noſtra vos eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis?</hi> are not you our deſtruction? yea, no queſtion, you are our deſtruction. Wherefore though many other thinges were amiſſe amongſt the people of the Iewes, yet becauſe they proceeded from the diſorder of the Temple, as the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect from the cauſe, according to the counſaile of God by the prohet <hi>Ezechiell, à ſanctuario meo incipite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 9.</note> Begin at my ſanctuary; and the rule which his Apoſtle Saint <hi>Peter</hi> lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of him, that <hi>iudgement muſt begin at the houſe of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.</note> he beginneth his reformation at the Temple of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:27798:8"/>
               <note place="margin">The fourth circumſtance.</note>But let vs conſider the fourth circumſtance what it was that he reformed there: <hi>Hee caſt out all thoſe that ſold, and bought in the Temple, and ouerthrew the tables of money-changers, and the ſeates of them that ſold doues.</hi> Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe abuſes, buying and ſelling, of ſheepe, and ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, and doues, and money-changers, and that in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, may ſeeme ſomewhat ſtrange vnto you, may it pleaſe you to vnderſtand, that according to the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God, all ſorts of people from all the regions of <hi>Iurie,</hi> came vp to this moſt royall and ample Temple, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially on feſtiuall daies, to offer ſacrifice vnto the Lord. The richer ſort offered oxen, goates, ſheepe, &amp;c. the poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer ſort, pigeons, and turtle doues, &amp;c. But it hapned of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes, that they which came far off, brought no ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with them; wherefore the Prieſts to make a prey of the people, as Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> noteth, ſold them-ſelues, or cauſed to be ſold by others, ſheepe, and oxen, and doues, &amp; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer was neceſſary for the ſacrifice: and for this mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizing in the Temple, had their pretence out of the letter of the law;<note place="margin">Deut. 14.</note> where they that dwelt farre off, were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to ſell their offerings at home, and with that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney buy oxen and ſheepe, &amp;c. when they came to <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> Now the Prieſts ſeemed to prouide for this law, that none that came farre off might want ſacrifices; but indeed vnder pretence of that, ſtudied their owne prophane profit and gaine.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe it happened that ſome came thither that were ſo poore, that they had no mony to buy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> offerings, they placed there money-changers, who vppon ſecuritie would lend them the mony: but becauſe vſury was forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by the law, &amp; yet they would make ſome gaine of their money they were contented to take ſmaller trifles, which would yeeld them money, as rayſons and apples, and ſuch kinde of ſtuffe, as they call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, thinking by this meanes to auoid the law; whereas the Prophet <hi>Ezechiel</hi> ſaith <hi>vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra a &amp; ſuperabundantiam non accipietis;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 22.</note> you ſhall not take either vſury or increaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:27798:8"/>Others that are learned are of opinion, that theſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney-changers, theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as they be called in the text, were placed there to change their monies that came to that place to buy their ſacrifices, as to change greater money for ſmaller, or good for ſiluer; or forraine money for currant money; and were called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignified an halfepenny, which was giuen for the change, which may be gathered to be more probable, becauſe Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> calleth them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Ioh. 2.</note> which ſignifieth ſmall money, and ſerueth for change; ſo that it ſhoulde ſeeme theſe money-changers, were ſuch as <hi>Caietane</hi> noteth to bee in <hi>Rome</hi> for ſuch purpoſes, <hi>in gradibus Diui Petri,</hi> vppon <hi>S. Peters</hi> ſtaires.</p>
            <p>Moreouer may it pleaſe you alſo to vnderſtand for your better inſtruction in this ſtory, and that you may perceiue what theſe abuſes were, that the name of the Temple is ſometimes taken properly and ſtrictly <hi>pro domo templi,</hi> for the body of the temple, which was diuided into two parts, as our churches are, one was called <hi>Sanctum,</hi> the holy place, where there was the Altar of incenſe, the Table, and the Candelſticke; and the other was <hi>Sanctum ſanctorum,</hi> the holy of holyeſt, where was the Arke of the Teſtament, and the two <hi>Cherubins:</hi> into that part that was called <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum,</hi> the Prieſts onely entred to offer incenſe, and none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; into the <hi>Sanctum ſanctorum</hi> the high Prieſt entred on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and that but once a yeare.</p>
            <p>Sometimes the Temple is taken more largely, and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth a certaine quadrangle compaſſed in with a wall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Temple; and it was called <hi>Atrium Sacerdotum,</hi> the Prieſtes Court, where there was an altar for burnt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings; and into this not onely the Prieſts did enter, but the Leuites alſo, who did helpe them to flea and waſh the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices: now at the gate of this Court the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſtood, and offered their ſacrifices to the Prieſtes. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to none of theſe places came our Sauiour; not into the <hi>Sanctum ſanctorum,</hi> becauſe he was not high Prieſt; not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Sanctum,</hi> becauſe he was no Prieſt; not into the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:27798:9"/>
Prieſts Court, becauſe he was neither Prieſt nor Leuite.</p>
            <p>But beſide theſe, there were two other places to pray in, <hi>ſub diuo,</hi> abroad in the aire; in one the men praid, in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the women praid: and theſe <hi>Atria</hi> or Courts were called by the name of the Temple; as in the <hi>Actes</hi> it is ſaid, that <hi>Peter and Iohn went into the Temple about the ninth hower to pray.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 3.</note> And this is the place which is noted heere by the name of the <hi>Temple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lyra ſuper. <hi>21.</hi> Matt.</note> and to be thus groſſely abuſed by the meanes of the Prieſts. Now our Sauiour, to ſhew his zeale to his Fathers houſe, and his authority togither with his power, as alſo to informe vs, that no temporall or baſe gaine ought to be exerciſed in Gods houſe, but to bee reckoned foule and vnhoneſt, whatſoeuer faire pretence it may carry with it: finally, to ſhew that nothing was fitte for that place, but holynes and prayers and deuotion <hi>he caſt out the buyers and ſellers, and the money-changers, and the ſeates of them that ſold doues, out of the Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now out of this fourth circumſtance among many things worthy the obſeruation, they that haue to doo with the reformation of the Church or Common-wealth, may learn not to take away the vſe of good things, becauſe they be abuſed, but to remoue the abuſe, and reſtore the thing to his proper nature and firſt inſtitution: For our Sauiour fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding theſe groſſe abuſes in the Temple, doth not offer to pul downe the Temple, or perſwade the Magiſtrates to turne it to prophane vſes, or to build them goodly pallaces or courts of the ruines of it;<note place="margin">Eraſm.</note> to conuert the veſſels of gold and ſiluer to their owne pleaſures, as <hi>Baltaſar</hi> did; or to the maintenance of their lawfull warres, or vnlawfull delights: but he taketh away the abuſes of it, he driueth out the buyers, and the ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and the money-changers; and that which was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for <hi>a houſe of prayer</hi> and ſeruice of God, hee reſtoreth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to the firſt inſtitution.</p>
            <p>For ſeeing all the eſtates of the world, the eſtate of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the eſtate of Prieſtes, and the eſtate of the Nobility, yea and the eſtate of the people, where they haue any eſtate, <hi>à paruis initijs ad maiora proficiunt,</hi> doe by degrees enlarge
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:27798:9"/>
their authorities, and of ſmall beginnings grow into great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, <hi>donec in vitium vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> luxurient,</hi> and at laſt run, ryot and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe their authority when it is at the higheſt. If in our refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations we ſhould not follow this patterne of our Sauiour, but remoue good thinges for the abuſe of them; many ſtrange, many dangerous, and vnnaturall alterations would enſue both in the Church and Common-wealth. And wee finde by experience, that this argument <hi>Ab abuſu, ad non vſum,</hi> From the abuſe of good things to the aboliſhing of them, as it hath bred hereſies and ſchiſmes in the Church; ſo alſo rebellions and treaſons in the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Manichees</hi> altogether condemned Chriſtianity, becauſe there were found many ill Chriſtians: to whome Saint <hi>Auſten</hi> anſwered,<note place="margin">Contra Fauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Veſtrum oculum maleuolus error in ſolam paleam noſtrae ſegetis ducet, nam &amp; triticum ibi citò in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deretur, ſi &amp; eſſe velletis.</hi> Your malicious errour carrieth your eye to the chaffe onely of our corne: you might as eaſily perceiue the wheat, if you were ſo diſpoſed. The <hi>Donatiſts</hi> refuſed the Sacraments, becauſe the Prieſts were wicked which adminiſtred them: to whom Saint <hi>Auſten</hi> ſaid, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe est vt ſemper erretis, quamdiu propter hominum vitia Dei ſacramenta violatis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Contra litt. Petil. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> You can neuer poſſibly be free from errour, ſo long as you violate the ſacraments of God for the faults of men. The <hi>Anabaptists</hi> would remooue Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Magiſtrates, becauſe many haue abuſed their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and gouernment: to whome we anſwere, though <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li abutuntur rebus bonis,</hi> Euill men abuſe good ordinances; yet, if a kingdome were not a lawfull ſtate and calling, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Dauid, Ioſias</hi> and the like, would not haue bin Kings: for <hi>Boni non vtuntur rebus malis,</hi> thoſe that are good meddle not with bad matters: And wee finde that the rent in the kingdome of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was becauſe,<note place="margin">3. Reg. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Rehoboam</hi> abuſed his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement: and the alteration of the ſtate of the <hi>Romans</hi> vnder the Kings, was becauſe, <hi>Quae honestè habere licebat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Saluſt in Cat.</note> 
               <hi>per turpitudinem abuti properabant.</hi> For the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by reaſon of their ignorance, <hi>inuincible ignorance,</hi> bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not able to diſcerne between the true vſe of that which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:27798:10"/>
is good, and the abuſe of it; nor between that fault that proceedeth <hi>ex natura facti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Th.</hi> 1. <hi>queſ.</hi> 41. <hi>art.</hi> 6.</note> out of the nature of the fact it ſelfe, becauſe it is <hi>malum ſimpliciter,</hi> ſimply euill, and that which proceedeth <hi>ex abuſu boni,</hi> from the abuſe of that which is good, which is <hi>malum per accidens,</hi> euill but by an accident; will allow of a tyranny, as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> noteth, which is the woorſt ſtate of Gouernement,<note place="margin">De bono coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gals cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſi regia clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ſubditos tractet,</hi> If hee handle the ſubiects with the cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency of a King; and condemne a Monarchy, the beſt kinde of gouernement, <hi>Si rex crudelitate tyrannica ſaeuiat,</hi> if being a King he ſhew the cruelty of a tyrant, beeing not able to diſcerne betweene the iuſt vſe of an vniuſt authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the vniuſt vſe of a iuſt authority. They will with <hi>Lycurgus</hi> roote out all the Vines in a Countrey, becauſe men will be drunke, and euen mad with wine; whereas <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> ſaith, they ſhould rather digge welles and fountaines neere vnto them; and as <hi>Plato</hi> counſelleth, <hi>Inſanum Deum alio ſobrio repreſſum, caſtigare;</hi> that is take away the abuſe by mixing ſome quantity of water with it. They will with <hi>Cotta,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Viues de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Cicero</hi> reporteth, condemne reaſon &amp; knowledge in men, becauſe oftentimes it is the cheefeſt inſtrument of ſin and iniquity, and beeing giuen vnto man as an excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie aboue other creatures, doth make him much woorſe than any brute beaſt.<note place="margin">De interiori domo Cap. <hi>50.</hi>
               </note> They will forbid reading and diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of ſtudy, becauſe as S. <hi>Bernard</hi> noteth, <hi>Prolixa lectio memoriam legentis obliterat,</hi> Ouer much reading hurteth the memory of the reader; not conſidering with S. <hi>Bernard</hi> that often times <hi>Crimen non eſt in rebus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>ſed in vſu agentis,</hi> the fault is not in the things, but in him that vſeth them: nor with S.<note place="margin">Aug. de doct. ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtin,</hi> that <hi>In multis non vſus rerum, ſed libido vtentis in culpa eſt,</hi> In many things not their vſe, but the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order of him that vſeth them muſt be blamed: nor that the rule is not,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. topic,</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Cuius abuſus malus eſt, ipſum quoque malum eſt;</hi> but <hi>Cuius vſus malus eſt, id eſt, per ſe malus eſt, ipſum quoque malum eſt,</hi> that which may bee abuſed is euill, but that which cannot be well vſed; which is the ſame which the Canoniſts haue,<note place="margin">Nauarus en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chir, cap, <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Si vſus principalis alicuius rei ſit mortifer,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:27798:10"/>
mortiferam quoque rem ipſam efficiet:</hi> that is, if the principall vſe of any thing be deadly, it ſhall make the thing it ſelfe of like nature.</p>
            <p>Now our Sauiour here teacheth them another leſſon, not to pull downe Churches for the abuſe of them, or the abuſe of the Prieſt; but reforme the abuſe and retaine the good vſe. And although our Sauior when the Iewes were incorrigible, and would not be reformed, nor repent them of that ſinne of ſinnes, the putting to death, to ſhamefull death, that innocent Lambe, the very Sonne of God, our Sauior Chriſt Ieſus, threatned the deſtruction of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and the miſerable captiuity of the whole Nation, and perfourmed it: So that <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> became as <hi>Iericho</hi> was an <hi>execrable thing;</hi> for although <hi>Iulian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſua 6.</note> and the <hi>Greacians</hi> and the <hi>Iewes,</hi> endeuoured to repaire it and build it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, yet it was impoſſible, by reaſon of earthquakes and fires from heauen, which conſumed the ſtuffe, and troubled the workmen, as <hi>Theoderet</hi> reporteth: yet this was but a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moouing of their candleſticke, as I may call it,<note place="margin">Theod lib. <hi>5.</hi> ca. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> not the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out of the Candle; a remoouing of the Temple of God and the Prieſthood to another Nation, that is, to the Gentiles; not an vtter ſubuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Churches &amp; eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call State; or to vſe our Sauiors words in this ſame Chap.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 43.</note> 
               <hi>A taking away of the Kingdome of God from them and giuing it to a Nation that ſhould bring foorth the fruites thereof;</hi> as when <hi>Saul</hi> became incorrigible, and abuſed his State, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> ſaid not, the Lord hath rent away the kingdome from <hi>Iſrael</hi> this day, and will haue no more Kings but Iudges, &amp;c. but, <hi>The Lord hath rent the kingdome of</hi> Iſrael <hi>from thee this day, and hath giuen it to thy neighbour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>who is better than thou:</hi> that is, hath remooued the inſufficient from the place of gouernment, and put in his roome one more ſufficient. To teach vs, that as for the ſinnes of Princes and abuſe of their State, the manner of gouernment is not altered by God, nor their priueledges abrogated, but the Office tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to a fitter perſon; ſo, for the abuſe of Churches and Church-men, neither the Churches ought to bee defaced
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:27798:11"/>
and ruined, nor the ſtate of the Cleargie to bee diſgraced and villified; but thoſe that are diſordered muſt bee diſpla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and their honours beſtowed vpon better men. For this is a leſſon ſet downe in the rules of the law, as an <hi>axiome</hi> or <hi>maxime</hi> in nature, &amp; not in a law poſitiue or humaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>6.</hi> decr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eg. iuris.</note> that, <hi>Semel Deo dedicatum, non eſt ad vſus humanos vlterius tranſferendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> That which hath beene once dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to God, is not any more to bee tranſferred to the vſes of men. And it ſeemeth to bee ſo euident by the light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that children acknowledge it as <hi>Plato</hi> confeſſeth; who ſpeaking of a truth as euident as he tooke it, as that two and two make foure, <hi>Nos dicimus</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quod pueri ſolent; Quae rectè data ſunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plat. Phileb.</note> 
               <hi>eripi non licet;</hi> We ſay as children vſe to doo: Thinges well giuen, muſt not be taken backe againe: and therfore no meruaile if it were a caſe ouer-ruled by the more ancient ſort of heathen Phyloſophers in their Courts of iuſtice,<note place="margin">Plin. <hi>2.</hi> Epiſt. lib. <hi>10</hi> Epiſt. <hi>74.</hi> and <hi>75.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Si facta aedes ſit, licèt collapſa ſit iam, religio tamen eius occupauit ſolum:</hi> If an houſe hath bene once dedicated to God, though it be fallen down and vtterly decayed, yet the ſoyle is holy, and the ground religious, and not to bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to ciuill or prophane vſes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The fift cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance.</note>The fifth circumſtance in the Fact, is the manner how our Sauiour performed this reformation, <hi>Hee caſt out them that ſold and bought, &amp;c.</hi> An extraordinary courſe is vſed by our Sauiour, and therefore the more obſeruable. For whereas in all other places and againſt all other ſinnes hee vſeth wordes, and reproofes and reprehenſions; and thoſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo tempered with humility, mildnes and gentlenes: Heere he vſeth force and execution, and externall diſcipline, and preſent correction, by caſting them out of the Temple, by making a whippe of ſmall cordes,<note place="margin">Iohn. 2.</note> and ſo whipping the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out; by ouerthrowing the tables of the money-changers, and the ſeates and chaires of them that ſold doues: and whereas he ſaith of himſelfe, that hee <hi>was ſent into the world, not to iudge the vvorld, but that the worlde might bee ſaued by him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn, 3.</note> yet in this caſe, in this ſinne, in this abuſe, and prophanation of the Temple, as it were forgetting his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:27798:11"/>
accuſtomed gentleneſſe, and the end of his comming, hee exerciſeth puniſhment, ſtriketh with a whippe, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth the tables, caſteth abroad the money, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, caſteth them out of the Temple; and that by himſelfe alone, and with his owne hands.</p>
            <p>If her excellent Maieſtie, beeing famous and renowned for her ſingular clemency, ſhoulde come to this Citty and with her own hands, puniſh a fault or miſdemeanor, it were a good argument that, that kind of ſinne were moſt odious vnto her; here our Sauior <hi>the Prince of peace</hi> and fountaine of mercy commeth to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and with his owne hands doth puniſh the abuſes, and the prophanations of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of GOD. <hi>Adam</hi> ſinned,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> and hee ſent his Angels or Cherubins to caſt him out of Paradiſe. The wicked So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites ſinned, and hee ſent his Angels,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.</note> and it rayned fire from heauen and conſumed them. The whold world cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted their way vpon earth,<note place="margin">Gen 7.</note> and hee ſent raine from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and deſtroyed them with a flood. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> would not harken to his voyce to let the people goe,<note place="margin">Exod 8.</note> and he ſent Frogs and Graſhopers &amp;c. and waſted his country.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by numbring his people, and hee ſent an Angell and ſmote them with peſtilence.<note place="margin">Dan. 13.</note> The Elders ſinned againſt <hi>Suſanna,</hi> and God ſent the Child <hi>Daniel</hi> to doe iudgement on them. Onely this ſinne of prophaning and abuſing his Temple, he correcteth and chaſteneth with his owne hands, he ſendeth not his Angels, hee ſendeth not fire, hee ſendeth not water, hee ſendeth not his Prophets, but hee commeth himſelfe and taketh puniſhment of them.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay; How could this bee, that our Sauiour Chriſt, being one man, and vnarmed, without a guard or ſouldiers after him, without any humane authority or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall calling, in the preſence of the Prieſts and the Scribes, who hated him with deadly hatred, and at that preſent time ſought after his life, who made profit of thoſe buiers and ſellers, who alſo were many in number, and moſt attentiue and greedy after their gaine, and had (as I ſaid before) an honeſt pretence out of the law for this their marchandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:27798:12"/>
notwithſtanding all theſe circumſtances, without tumult, without noiſe, without contradiction or reſiſtance, hee ſhould bee able to caſt them all together out of the Temple?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hierom ſuper <hi>21.</hi> Math,</note>But the anſwere is plaine, That it was done by a miracle, as the ancient Fathers do iointly teſtifie: &amp; S. <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaith, that this was the greateſt of all his miracles. Some thinke ſaith he, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt miracle he wrought, was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> raiſing of <hi>Lazarus</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead; &amp; ſome thinke that the giuing of ſight to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blind was the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt miracle; ſome the voice that was heard at <hi>Iordane</hi> when he was baptized; ſome his transfiguration in the mountaine, where he ſhewed his triumphant glory &amp; maieſty: but ſaith he, of al the ſignes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer he wrought, this ſeemeth moſt miraculous in mine eie, that one man at that time contemptible, ſo far foorth vile &amp; baſe in their eies, that he was afterwards crucified; in deſpight of Scribes &amp; Prieſts, could caſt out with whips ſuch a multitude of men and cattle, which a pretty army of men could haue hardly performed: but (ſaith he) <hi>Igneum quiddam &amp; ſidereum radiabat in oculis eius;</hi> There was ſome fiery and ſtarry brightnes that gliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in his eies; and the maieſty of his Diuinity did ſhine in his face: ſo that neither Scribes, nor Phariſies, nor Prieſts, nor buiers, nor ſellers,<note place="margin">Ori. ſupe <hi>2,</hi> Iob.</note> durſt reſiſt &amp; withſtand him. And S. <hi>Origen</hi> ſaith, that this was a greater miracle then the turning of water into wine, becauſe their <hi>inanimata materia ſubſistit;</hi> a matter without life &amp; ſoule doth yeeld vnto him: but in this, <hi>tot millium hominum do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantur ingenia;</hi> hee daunteth the hearts and courages of thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of men. For you ſhall vnderſtand, that ſome miracles were wrought vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodies of men, which we moſt admire, becauſe they are ſubiect to the ſight of our eies: &amp; ſome vpon the mindes of men, <hi>quantùm ad immutandas inferiores vires,</hi> concerning the change of their inferiour faculties, as the Schoolemen ſay; which though they were more miraculous, yet to vs they ſeeme not ſo. And this diſtinction may bee gathered out of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> where he ſaith;<note place="margin">Heb. 2.</note> that God bare witnes to Chriſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>by ſignes and wonders, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by diuers powers,</hi> which wrought vpon the mindes and ſoules of men. The mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles which he wrought vpon bodies are obſerued by you al, but the miracle which he wrought vpon their minds &amp; ſoules were
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:27798:12"/>
theſe &amp; the like: firſt, the informing of his Diſciples with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge &amp; vnderſtanding,<note place="margin">Luk. 21.</note> 
               <hi>I wil giue you a mouth &amp; wiſdome where againſt all your aduerſaries ſhall not be able to ſpeake or reſiſt.</hi> And therfore it is ſaid in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Actes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act, 4.</note> that <hi>when the Iewes ſaw the conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of Peter and Iohn, &amp; vnderſtood that they were vnlearned men, and without knowledge,</hi> admirabanter, <hi>they thought it a miracle.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math 9.</note> The ſecond is the calling of <hi>Mathew;</hi> for as ſoone as he ſaid, <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me,</hi> though he ſate at the receipt of coſtome, yet preſently <hi>he roſe vp and followed him: Fulgur diuinae Maieſtatis videntem ad ſe traxit;</hi> The lightning of his diuine Maieſty drew him vnto him ſo ſoone as he did but ſee him. The 3. is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel of <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 18.</note> wher as ſoone as he ſaid to the band of men &amp; officers that came with <hi>Iudas</hi> to apprehend him, <hi>I am he; they went backward, &amp; fel to the ground:</hi> S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> writing vpon that place, ſaith it was a miracle. The forth is in S. <hi>Lukes</hi> Goſpel,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Trae.</hi> 112. <hi>ſupe. Iob.</hi> Luk. 4.</note> where they of the Sinagogue led him to the edge of an hill, to thruſt him downe headlong, <hi>but Ieſus paſſed through the midſt of them, and went his way:</hi> where S. <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> ſaith; <hi>Stare in medio inſidiantium &amp; non apprehendi,</hi> To ſtand in the midſt of thoſe that way-laid him &amp; not to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, ſhewed his Diuinity, and was a miracle. Finally, as I haue ſhewed you before, with this facility to caſt out the buiers, and ſellers, &amp;c. and not to be reſiſted, argued the power of his Diuinity, and was a miracle. And this of the fifth circumſtance.</p>
            <p>I amplifie this poynt, and vrge all theſe circumſtances of our Sauiours force, and extraordinary violence vſed in this place, and the miraculous perfourming of it; to ſhew vnto you how odious this ſinne is, of prophaning the Church of GOD with buying and ſelling. And no queſtion, if this merchandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing (which had ſo faire a pretence for it as the letter of the law, &amp; the eaſe and benifit of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole nation) was ſo odious to our Sauiour Chriſt; our merchandizing, and buying &amp; ſelling in the Church of God, cannot be leſſe odious and offenſiue to him.</p>
            <p>For our buying and ſelling in the Church of GOD, our <hi>Symonie,</hi> as wee call it, hath no pretence for it in the lawe of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> nor in the lawe of the Goſpell, nor in Eccleſiaſticall or Canon lawes, nor in the Ciuill and Nationall lawes of any Countrey. The law of <hi>Moyſes</hi> prouided ſo liberally
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:27798:13"/>
for the Prieſts and the whole family of the <hi>Leuites,</hi> by the <hi>free citties,</hi> and the <hi>demaines</hi> which were allowed them in euery Tribe, that there was neither vſe nor abuſe of buying and ſelling till <hi>Ieroboams</hi> time,<note place="margin">3. Reg. 13.</note> who <hi>erected an altar against the altar of GOD, and made of the lowest of the people (that would fill his hand) idolatrous prieſts.</hi> In the new law of the new Teſtament there was <hi>gratis accepiſtis, gratis date;</hi> the Apoſtles receiued their gifts freely, and gaue them free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; the people receiued the word freely, and freely of their owne accord they laid downe the price of their land at the Apoſtles feete. The Eccleſiaſticall and Ciuill lawes forbid nothing with greater regard, ſince the Church was endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with peculiar maintenance, than the buying and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Spirituall offices, and Eccleſiaſticall perferments: and I know none, either ancient Father, or Schoole-man, or late Writer, which applieth not this Scripture, and this Action of our Sauiour Chriſt, to our Simoniacall buying and ſelling of orders and offices in Chriſtian Churches. So that if all councels and ancient reuerend Biſhoppes, which had the conſtituting or confirming of Eccleſiaſticall lawes be not deceiued, this <hi>Simonie</hi> is a wrong to the ſtate of the Church: if all good Princes and Stateſmen, and Parliaments bee not deceiued, who haue the making and eſtabliſhing of Statute Lawes, this <hi>Simonie</hi> is preiudiciall to a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale: if all interpreters be not deceiued, it is a ſinne againſt the law of God, and ſeuerely chaſtiſed in this place by our Sauiour Chriſt, either miſtically and figuratiuely, or by neceſſary conſequence. For if thoſe things which by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture were vendible, as ſheepe and oxen, and to that purpoſe, to offer them in ſacrifice to God, might not be bought and ſould in the houſe of GOD or the precincts of it; much leſſe may offices Eccleſiaſticall, or Tythes, or the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Gods Miniſters, which by nature are not ſaleable, be bought or ſold in the Church of God.</p>
            <p>For what? If the ſinne of <hi>Simon Magus</hi> (of whom this fault hath denomination) conſiſted in buying onely, and not in ſelling of that which was ſpiritual; ſeeing buying and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:27798:13"/>
ſelling are both in a predicament (for nothing is bought but that which is ſold, <hi>&amp; contrà</hi>) and the Apoſtles had ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as greeuouſly in ſelling, as <hi>Simon</hi> did in buying: and the Schoole-men ſay well,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Th.</hi> 22. <hi>quest.</hi> 100. <hi>art.</hi> 1.</note> that <hi>Vendentes conformantur Simoni in intentione ſi non in actu;</hi> Sellers are conformed to <hi>Simon Magus</hi> in purpoſe, though not in action; becauſe he would haue bought the holy Ghoſt, to ſell his miracles. May not the Church impoſe one name to both theſe ſinnes, which are couſin germaines, nay brother germanes, as well as buying and ſelling ſhould bee comprehended vnder the word of merchandizing? or that, <hi>ſeruus, vas, ager, arbor, pecus,</hi> ſhould be contained vnder the name of <hi>pecunia,</hi> as <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> noteth in his Bookes of Chriſtian Learning?</p>
            <p>Againe; If the ſinne of <hi>Simon Magus</hi> properly conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the buying of a ſpirituall thing, of the working of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, which is meerely ſpirituall; as the gift of preaching or the gift of prophecying; and the gift of preaching and the maintenance allotted for it, by what name or title ſo-euer you call it, concurre to the making of a perfect Preacher, as the ſoule and body to the making of a perfect man; ſo that as the ſoule ſeperated from the body, though it liueth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> Si quis obiecerit.</note> yet it liueth not <hi>corporaliter,</hi> bodily; ſo Preaching ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the maintenance, though it liueth, yet it liueth not <hi>ciuiliter</hi> or <hi>humaniter,</hi> as ciuilitie and humanitie would it ſhould, as GOD hath appointed it to liue in this world: may not the buying and ſelling of a Biſhopricke or Benefice, which is <hi>annexum quiddam ſpiritualibus,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what annexed to ſpirituall affaires, bee accompted <hi>Simonie;</hi> when not onely the ſoule of man is ſaid to liue, but the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die alſo which is <hi>annexum quiddam,</hi> is ſaid to liue <hi>ex vnione animae,</hi> by the vnion of the ſoule: when, not hee onely that killeth the ſoule is ſaid to doo murther, but hee alſo that kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the body which hath no life but by meanes of the ſoule; when not hee onely is ſaid to ſinne againſt the Maieſtie of a Prince, who offereth iniurie to his perſon, or crowne, but hee alſo that doth violence to thoſe things which are annexed to his crowne and dignitie?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:27798:14"/>This ſelling and buying in the Church of God, which by the generall conſent of interpreters, Fathers and School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, is here puniſhed by our Sauiour Chriſt, and is iuſtly called <hi>Simonie,</hi> and a true branch of the ſinne of <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> is ſo common and vſuall in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that I muſt needs ſay, that either you eſteeme it not as a ſinne, or if you take it for a ſinne, ſince our Sauiour is aſcended into Heauen, you thinke there is no GOD to puniſh you for it.</p>
            <p>To hold it no ſinne, is to hold the hereſie of <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> (for ſo it is called) that is,<note place="margin">Caiet. in <hi>8.</hi> Act.</note> to thinke that the holy Ghoſt may be bought and ſould; for when <hi>Officium curae animaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> praecipuum ac ſpiritualiſſimum Dei donum ſit;</hi> The office of the charge of ſoules is an eſpeciall and moſt ſpirituall gift of God: to buy or to ſell the office of the charge of ſoules in generall, that is, to buy or ſell Orders, or to buy and ſell the office of the charge of theſe or thoſe ſoules; that is, to buy or ſell a Preſentation, is <hi>Simonie,</hi> and that in his owne nature, and not becauſe it is forbidden by Eccleſiaſticall or Ciuill Law. And it is not onely <hi>vulnus cancroſum,</hi> as Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> calleth it, a wound that hath a canker in it, and therefore will creepe along through euery ioynt of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of a Common-wealth, as wee finde by our miſerable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience,<note place="margin">1. q, 1. <hi>reperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur.</hi>
               </note> and ſo requireth <hi>ignitum ferrum,</hi> a hot coulter or ſharpe ſword, that is, the extremity of ciuill puniſhment; nor <hi>execrabile flagitium</hi> onely, a deteſtable ſinne, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>anathematis opprobrio condemnandum,</hi> to be condemned &amp; curſed with Excommunication, the higheſt cenſure of the Church;<note place="margin">Act. 8.</note> but it is that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that <hi>wickedneſſe</hi> or <hi>ſinfulneſſe</hi> that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh of, and that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that <hi>bond</hi> or <hi>bundle of iniquity,</hi> that containeth many ſinnes faſt chained together: which argue, that <hi>the hart is not right,</hi> and from which wee may pray to bee deliuered, not ſimply as from other ſinnes, but <hi>if it be poſſible,</hi> as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled <hi>Simon Magus pray vnto God, that if it bee poſſible this thought of thy hart may be forgiuen thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But foraſmuch as ſince the time, that good Chriſtians
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:27798:14"/>
are degenerated into cunning politicians, it is not ſo much regarded, what is good for the ſtate of the Church, as what is fitting and behoofefull for a Common-wealth; nor ſuch reckoning made of eternall reward, or eternall puniſhment, as of preſent pleaſure &amp; of puniſhment inflicted on our body, or goods: and we ſay with the Policitians,<note place="margin">Aug. de ciuit. Dei li. <hi>2</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pace ſecura ſit reſp. floreat copijs referta, victorijs glorioſa, &amp; quid ad nos?</hi> If there be peace &amp; plenty and proſperity, what care we for the ſtate of the Church? I will giue you ſome reaſons amongſt many, why this ſelling and buying in the Church, which is the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vndooing of the ſtate of the Clergy, as it is not lawfull by the word of God; ſo not tolerable in regard of the policy of a Chriſtian Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, as much as in it lyeth, it taketh away the ſociety <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and fellowſhippe of mankinde, wherein conſiſteth a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men-wealth. For if wee ſhall bee ſo affected, that euery man for his owne commodity, will rob and ſpoyle another man, the ſociety of mankind, which of all things is moſt naturall, muſt needes bee diſſolued: and if wee ſhall bee ſo affected, that one ſtate in a Common-wealth will by all meanes endeuour to eate vp another, that deformity will grow in the Common-wealth, that would happen in the body of a man in the like caſe; for if the legs ſhould challenge and enioy all that nouriſhment which ſhould goe to the armes, the one part would be vnweldy by his greatnes, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnprofitable by his weakenes.</p>
            <p>It is well knowen and confeſſed, that the ſtate of the Clergy in euery good Chriſtian Common-wealth, hath had his lot and portion, not onely ſpirituall in the Lord, but alſo temporall in the Common-wealth, being an eſtate of men, as of the beſt deſert, if they do their duties; ſo not to be fed by the ayre, as the <hi>Cameleons</hi> are, but by the fruits and increaſe which proceede from the earth: and therefore they haue had allotted them by the law of nature, as <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech</hi> had; by the law of <hi>Moyſes</hi> as the Prieſts had; and by the confirmation of our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>haec oportet fieri,</hi> theſe things muſt bee done; and by ciuill and prouinciall
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:27798:15"/>
lawes in Chriſtianity, not onely the Tythes of the fruite of the earth; becauſe they haue bellies to be fed, and backs to bee clothed,<note place="margin">Num. 35.</note> and families to bee maintained: but they had their Citties and their lands belonging to them among the Iewes, and their parts in the ſacrifice and offerings: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Chriſtians their demaines, and temporalties; becauſe that ſtate was not anarchicall, or without authoritie and iuriſdiction. Laſtly, they had their ſpeciall priuiledges, namely not to ſerue in the tabernacle before 25.<note place="margin">Num. 8.</note> yeare old, not after 50. their Cities of refuge and Sanctuaries, &amp;c. In the famine of <hi>Aegipt</hi> they had an ordinarie allowance of <hi>Pharaoh;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 35.</note> ſo that when hee bought all the land of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects in <hi>Aegipt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 47.</note> yet the Prieſts land was not ſolde: ſo great were their priuiledges among the Heathen.</p>
            <p>Now if their Chriſtian priuiledges which haue beene many, ſhall be made voide, againſt the rule of the 12. Tables, <hi>Priuilegia ne irroganto,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lud. Charend. ad Leg. antiq. Rom.</note> let them not infringe the Priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges:<note place="margin">Caſſiod lib <hi>2.</hi> epist. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> and againſt all reaſon when <hi>Theodoricus</hi> ſaid, <hi>Intra regulas conſtituti iuris non debet munificentia principum ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctari,</hi> the bounty of Princes ought not to bee ſtraightned within the bounds of the lawe; if where <hi>aequalitas</hi> is not <hi>aequitas,</hi> that is equity ioined with equalitie, the maintenance of all dignitie, and ſuperiority and authority be taken away, which will breede contempt; for as vertue is diſcouraged without rewarde, ſo authoritie is diſarmed without iuſt maintenance; finally, if thoſe neceſſaries which ſhould maintaine nature, which is contented with a little courſe cloath for the back, and courſe bread for the belly, bee retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by force or fine ſleight from that ſtate, or a great part of it, which is ordained as the Sunne is, <hi>ad continuos curſus,</hi> to continuall labour and trauaile in the houſe of God; and not onely taken from them, but giuen to a nation which bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth worſe fruite: it is out of all doubt, that as when one ſerpent eateth another <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a dragon is engendred which deuoureth all; ſo when one State eateth vp another, it bringeth foorth a monſtrous and vnnaturall ſtate in the common-wealth, and ſo by conſequent a dangerous change.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:27798:15"/>
So that wee are much to feare, that as before the comming of our Sauiour in the fleſh, the <hi>Romane</hi> Common-wealth being changed by little and little, <hi>ex pulcherrimâ &amp; optimâ,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de ciuit. Dei. li. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>peſſima ac flagitioſiſſima facta est;</hi> ſo the Common-wealth of <hi>England</hi> and of Chriſtianitie, by this foule ſinne of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie</hi> and Sacriledge, before the ſecond comming of our Sauiour, of a moſt religious and well ordered Common-wealth, will become irreligious and ſimoniacall.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this buying and ſelling in the Church of God,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> will make barren and like <hi>deſolate and forſaken Widowes</hi> the two Vniuerſities, the two fruitfull Mothers and full of Children, though now readie to giue vp the ghoſt, and powre out their ſoules in their Mothers boſomes. For if we that bee bred vp in learning, ſuffer in our childhood in the Grammar ſchooles <hi>magnum &amp; graue malum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. confeſ. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> a great and greeuous affliction (Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> compareth it to <hi>the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of martyrdome</hi>) and when wee come to the Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, if wee liue of the Colledges allowance, are, as <hi>Phalaris</hi> obiected to the <hi>Leontines,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epist.</hi> 53.</note> 
               <hi>needy of all things but hunger and feare;</hi> or if we be maintained but partly by our parents coſt, doo expend in neceſſarie main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, bookes, and degrees, before wee come to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, fiue hundred pounds, or a thouſand markes. If by this price of the expence of our time, our bodies and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, our ſubſtance and patrimonies, wee cannot purchaſe thoſe ſmall rewardes which are ours by law, and the right of inheritance, a poore Parſonage or a poore Vicarage, of fortie or fiftie pound a yeare; but wee muſt pay to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron for the leaſe of a life (a ſpent and out-worne life) ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in annuall penſion, or aboue the rate of a Copy-hold, and that with the hazard of the loſſe of our ſoules, by ſimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and periurie, and the forfeiture of all our ſpirituall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments in <hi>eſſe</hi> and in <hi>poſſe,</hi> both preſent and to come: what father after a while will bee ſo improuident, to bring vp his ſonne to his great charge, to this neceſſarie beggerie? What Chriſtian will bee ſo irreligious, as to bring vp his ſonne in that courſe of life, which by probabilitie of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:27798:16"/>
(<hi>quae cogit ad turpia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iuuenal.</note> enforcing to ſinne) will entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle him in ſimonie and periurie? When as the Poet ſaith; <hi>Inuitatus ad haec, aliquis de ponte negabit.</hi> A beggars brat ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from a bridge where hee ſitteth in begging, if hee knew the inconuenience, had cauſe to refuſe it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Obiections anſwered.</note>But you will ſay, that learning is to be deſired, and will be deſired for it ſelfe; becauſe as the <hi>Stoicks</hi> ſay, <hi>Doctrina est pretium ſibi,</hi> Learning is her owne recompence: and the Miniſter muſt conſider <hi>fructum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.</note> 
               <hi>non datum,</hi> the good that he doth, not the reward hee muſt haue: and therefore though this be a fault, yet no danger thereby of decay of learning. For the former, it is moſt true, that Learning is <hi>Lux animi, &amp; oblectatio vitae,</hi> the light of the minde, and delight of the life, and for it ſelfe to bee deſired; but of Gentlemen, who can liue without it; and of Stoickes and Philoſophers, which had no paſſions, which liued as ſoules without bodies, ſo farre in loue with the food of the one, that they tooke no regarde what became of the other. But if Gentlemen one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhould bee learned, a competent meaſure would ſerue their turne, the dephts of profeſſions are aboue their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours, they are ſo painefull: and you ſhall finde as few Schollers that doo reach to that height of Philoſophie, as to feed their mindes and to ſtarue their bodies, as you ſhall finde Gentlemen that are come to that height of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, <hi>to forſake all and follow Christ,</hi> or <hi>to loue their enemies and ſtudie their good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Romanes,</hi> who made <hi>Aedes honori &amp; virtuti ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mellas,</hi> that is, ioyned the Churches of Honour and Vertue the one cloſe to the other; and thoſe wiſe men who vpon ſepulchres and monuments engraued theſe titles, <hi>Virtuti &amp; Honori,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Symmac. lib. <hi>1.</hi> epist. <hi>37.</hi>
               </note> to Vertue and Honour; and our Founders and Benefactors, who appointed <hi>opulenta praemia literarum profeſſoribus,</hi> plentifull rewardes to the profeſſing of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:<note place="margin">Symmac. lib. <hi>10.</hi> Epist. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> they knew well enough, that <hi>Non deficit ſtudium, quod praemium largius habet;</hi> and that <hi>Virtus aemula, aelitur exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plo honoris alieni;</hi> Studie is neuer ſcant, where the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence is large; and vertue which is euermore in aemulation,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:27798:16"/>
is fed by the example of honor in other men. And againe on the other ſide, that learning would bee much diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,<note place="margin">A. Gel. petijt ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi aes dari <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Caſſiod.</note> if Schollers ſhould come to Gentlemen as the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher came to <hi>Herode</hi> to begge a penny to buy him bread; becauſe <hi>Probata virtus inhonora ceſſat,</hi> Vertue though it be commended, yet if it bee not honored and rewarded will ſoone be diſcouraged.</p>
            <p>For the latter, that we muſt not ſeeke <hi>datum</hi> but <hi>fructum,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> it is moſt true: But that law or reaſon that bindeth vs to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for your good, bindeth you to prouide ſufficiently for vs: <hi>Dignus est operarius mercede ſua,</hi> The workman is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of his hire. That law that bindeth him that laboureth to <hi>miniſter vnto you ſpirituall things,</hi> bindeth you to <hi>admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter vnto him corporall things,</hi> and not ſell them to him: <hi>ſi ſpiritualium eorum participes facti ſunt gentiles:</hi> if Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen bee partakers of their <hi>ſpirituall things, they must ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter vnto them worldly things:</hi> for as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.</note> hee was <hi>debitor illis,</hi> a debter vnto all; ſo on the other ſide,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores eorum ſunt,</hi> they are debters to the Apoſtles. And this is the diuiſion ſpoken of by the Sonne of <hi>Sirach; In diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one ſortis da &amp; accipe,</hi> giue and take, not ſell and take.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 14.</note> And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calleth it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. <hi>to communicate one with another after the manner of giuing and receiuing:</hi> to ſignifie (ſaith <hi>Caietan</hi> vppon that place) that the maintenance of the Cleargie is due <hi>ſecundùm rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones dati &amp; accepti;</hi> which therefore ſhould be <hi>Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones &amp; Commutationes,</hi> not <hi>Venditiones.</hi> And as in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, though wee owe our ſelues and all our ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours to our Prince and Countrey, <hi>Seruitia tamen per mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derata compendia prouocantur;</hi> yet ſome reaſonable conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration pulleth on our ſeruice; ſo alſo, though wee owe our ſelues and our labours to your ſaluation and aedification, and <hi>not to preach is a woe vnto vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.</note> and <hi>if I doo it willingly I haue my reward,</hi> the encreaſe of grace, the encreaſe of knowledge, and euerlaſting life, <hi>Euge bone ſerue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 25.</note> Well done good ſeruant, that is, a reward ſpirituall, a reward at Gods hands; yet for all that <hi>ſeruitia, &amp;c.</hi> our endeuours are ſtirred
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:27798:17"/>
vp with temporall rewards,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caſſ.</hi> 2, 11.</note> and neceſſary maintenance: and not only ours but other mens, who by our preferments, or at leaſt iuſt maintenance, may bee encouraged to this kind of calling. For as Mariage is honoured, why? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by that, <hi>reparatio poſteritatis acquiritur</hi> poſterity is kept in reparation: ſo our labours and callings muſt be honoured and regarded; becauſe not out of our loynes (as in <hi>Moyſes</hi> law proceedeth the ſeed of the Prieſthood) but out of our honours and preferments.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Another Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection anſw.</note>But you will ſay; This complaint needeth not, for many of the Cleargy are rich enough; and what eſtate is there in the world, but ſome of that calling doo liue in pouertie? To which I anſwere; That in what eſtate ſoeuer prodigali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or ſupine negligence is found, there pouerty will follow, and no remedie for it. But there is no calling within this Common-wealth wherein a painfull and induſtrious man may not liue decently and plentifully in that kinde of func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, except only in the Miniſtery: where, if they haue not money to buy them a Benefice, or preferment as we call it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they muſt liue of the almes of the poore of the pariſh, for reading ſome Lecture, as the Popiſh prieſts did of Dirrges and Maſſes; and haue their collection together with the old and the lame, and the blinde, and ſuch as are a burthen to the common-wealth. <hi>Oh</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard) what a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe order is this,</hi> coeleſtibus terrena mercari, <hi>to buy earthly with heauenly things? How much better were it, and more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to reaſon,</hi> vt pro carnali victu carnalia opera exerce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; nec fierent inuerſores rerum, aut inhonorarent ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le miniſterium; <hi>that they ſhould vſe bodily labour for bodily food without either changing the nature of things, or diſcredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their ſpirituall calling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for thoſe that are rich in the Clergy, the number (God knoweth) is very ſcant; and thoſe either
<q>Antiqui Heroës nati melioribus annis,</q>
which began with the beginning of her Maieſties reigne, when Benefices went a begging as Miniſters doe now; or thoſe whoſe beſt reuenew is parſimony and miſerable
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:27798:17"/>
diet, without hoſpitality; or els thoſe, who are enriched by land or other patrimony left vnto them by their parents or friends. And yet the greateſt part of theſe, who by their titles of dignity and outward appearance ſeeme rich vnto you, they haue <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a needy kinde of wealth, and eſtate vneſtabliſhed;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſeſs.</hi> 12.</note> or as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> calleth it <hi>copioſam inopiam, &amp; ignominioſam gloriam,</hi> a plentifull penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and inglorious glorie. Their dignities and honors for the moſt part are titular, like the Archdeaconrie of <hi>London</hi> in King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeconds daies:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epist.</hi> 151.</note> which <hi>Petrus Bleſenſis</hi> reported to <hi>Innocentius</hi> then Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> to bee <hi>Draco non habens vnde poſſit viuere niſi vento,</hi> A Dragon (a ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly name or title, <hi>the Archdeacon of London</hi>) not hauing wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to liue, except of winde: for ſaith he, <hi>Ille honos est in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, &amp; nndis, &amp; puris intellectibus,</hi> That preferment ſtandeth in onely, and naked, and pure ſuppoſals. So that if the Cleargie may take denomination of the greater part, of an hundred for one, it is a poore Cleargy; and hereafter when the Prince or the State ſhall haue need of their purſes, they muſt anſwere with Saint <hi>Peter; Argentum &amp; aurum non eſt mihi,</hi> Siluer and gold haue we none, but that which wee haue, we will readily afford; a praier or a bleſſing, a lecture or a ſermon.</p>
            <p>Wherefore to conclude this point, though learning of it ſelfe be neuer ſo precious, yet if ſtudents after they haue ſpent their time, their ſpirits, their liues, their patrymonies for the good of the Church or common-wealth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caſſ</hi> 2, 28.</note> ſhall bee thus neglected, nay skorned and deſpiſed (for <hi>exprobrata militia creditur, quae irremunerata tranſitur,</hi> his ſeruice in the Warres, his ſeruice in the Church, his ſeruice in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth is deſpiſed, as baſe, which is paſſed ouer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a reward) we ſhall not neede <hi>Iulians</hi> Edict, or <hi>Domitians</hi> law, good arts of themſelues will go into baniſhment.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, this buying and ſelling in the Church of GOD, will procure an vnſufficient and an vnlearned Miniſterie; for <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> by this meanes <hi>Strenuus &amp; ſegnis fato potiuntur eodem,</hi> the learned and the vnlearned are in like poſſibility to haue the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:27798:18"/>
preſentation at the patrons hands. <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe if hee can but ſpeake, if he come laden with coyne, ſhall bee preferred before <hi>Balaam</hi> his maiſter,<note place="margin">In laudibus Baſil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> if hee were as honeſt as hee was wiſe. And wee finde it already by experience, that as <hi>Greg. Naz.</hi> ſaid, if there bee a <hi>Samuel</hi> amongſt our Prophets, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, who is a ſeer as they called him, or a learned man; there is a <hi>Saul</hi> alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a baſe and an ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Prophet: by which meanes that order and calling which is <hi>in toto Chriſtianiſmo</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> the moſt reuerend and holy calling in all Chriſtianity, is become <hi>in toto Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſmo</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the moſt baſe and ridiculous calling in all Chriſtianity. Wherefore though the Romans thought it ſtood with their Common-wealth,<note place="margin">Patere.</note> 
               <hi>manere rudem Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiorum intellectum,</hi> that the Corinthians ſhould continue in rudeneſſe and ignorance; and though the Papiſts thought it good, and to ſtand with the policie of their Church, to keepe the people in blind ſimplicity: yet it cannot ſtand ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the policie of any Chriſtian Church or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, to haue ignorant teachers, ignorant Prieſts, ignorant Preachers; but ſeeing it is a curſe which God threatneth in his diſpleaſure to diſordered Common-wealths, <hi>&amp; erit ſicut populus, ſic &amp; ſacerdos,</hi> that the Prieſts ſhould be either as wicked or as ignorant as the people are, and this buying and ſelling effecteth this curſe, it ſeemeth moſt inconuenient for a Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, this buying and ſelling in the Church of God, this <hi>Simony,</hi> doth remoue all hoſpitality, and all meanes of hoſpitality from the ſtate of the Clergie, which doth not onely hinder and hold backe the fruites of our preaching, becauſe as Saint <hi>Gregorie</hi> noteth, <hi>Egentis mentem doctrinae ſermo non penetrat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Pastor.</note> 
               <hi>ſi hunc apud eius animum manus miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiae non commendat;</hi> The word of inſtruction dooth not pearce the minde of the needie, vnleſſe the hand of mercie doo further commend it vnto him: and ſecondly hinder vs from that great bleſſing &amp; commodity that <hi>Caſſiodore</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caſſiod.</hi> 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>Nonnulla pauperibus largiendi,</hi> Of giuing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to the poore: but thirdly, it is alſo iniurious to the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:27798:18"/>
Common-wealth; for as <hi>Tacitus</hi> noteth, there commonly followeth <hi>diſſolutio imperii ſi fructus quibus Reſp. ſuſtinetur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Annal.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>diminuuntur;</hi> a diſſolution of the State, when the fruites and reuenewes are diminiſhed, which maintaine the Common-wealth. Now, ſeeing hoſpitalitie is the beſt reuenew which is left to comfort and relieue the poorer ſort, which abound at this time in this Common-wealth; they are very iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to this State, who make not onely the ſuperfluitie of the wealth of the Cleargie, which are <hi>bona pauperum,</hi> the goods of the poore, but the very neceſſary maintenance of the Preachers themſelues, which are <hi>bona Chriſti,</hi> the goods of Chriſt; the goods of Gentlemen or Nobilitie.</p>
            <p>Fiftly. This buying and ſelling in the Church of God,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> this <hi>Simonie,</hi> if it doe not effect a diſſolution of this State; yet it doth foreſhew and portend ſome great euill to enſue. For wee read in the Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtorie,<note place="margin">Socrat. lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> that when cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine fugitiue ſlaues prophaned the Church by murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring one Prieſt, and wounding another; one that ſtood by ſuddainly vttered theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>that the prophanation of the Church did foreſhew no good to enſue;</hi> and hee alleadged for the confirmation of it two verſes out of a Greeke Poet,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </q>
               <hi>Nam ſaepè ſigna talia dari ſolent, cùm ſacra foedum templa polluit ſcelus.</hi> And ſaith <hi>Socrates, Hee that ſaid thus was not deceiued; for it foreſhewed troubles and diuiſions among the people, and the baniſhment of him that was authour of them.</hi> And we finde, that not long after this prophanation of the Temple, this buying and ſelling of oxen, and ſheepe, &amp;c. and the buying and ſelling of the Prieſt-hood which for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney was now become annuall; the deſtruction of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> enſued, and the diſperſion of the whole Nation: And the flouriſhing Kingdomes and Churches of <hi>Graecia</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menia</hi> were forſaken of God, and became ſubiect to the <hi>Turkes,</hi> when they began to maintaine this hereſie,<note place="margin">Alph. de Caſt.</note> 
               <hi>Licere res Eccleſiaſticas vendere;</hi> that it was lawful to ſell the goods
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:27798:19"/>
of the Church. And it is a receiued obſeruation among our Writers, that <hi>Eccleſia &amp; Imperium pariter defecerunt,</hi> when the Church began to bee prophaned by <hi>Simonie</hi> and <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> the Empire began to bee greatly eclipſed. And what elſe can we looke for after this prophanation of buying and ſelling in the Church of God, but ſome curſe to enſue; when <hi>Eccleſiaſtica poſſident Laici,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard. epiſt. <hi>224.</hi>
               </note> holy places &amp; holy things are poſſeſſed by prophane men, as Saint <hi>Barnard</hi> ſaith, who inſteed of Prayers which the Prieſt ſhould offer, doo ſend vp into heauen daily ſacrifices, <hi>quotidianas hoſtias,</hi> not peace offerings, <hi>ſed clamores pauperum, lachrymas viduarum, plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus orphanorum;</hi> The cryes of the poore, the teares of the widowes, and the miſerable complaints of children and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes?</p>
            <p>Wherefore, ſeeing this buying and ſelling in the Church is ſo heinous in the ſight of God, and ſo inconuenient for a Common-wealth; giue mee leaue (honorable Lords, and reuerent Fathers of the Cleargie) who haue your places of ſtate and dignitie, both in the Church and Common-wealth; giue me leaue in all humilitie I beſeech you, not to exhort you to that, which I hope you doo already; nor to dehort you from that fault, from which I am perſwaded that ſome of you are as free and innocent as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was; but to counſell him that ſtandeth, to take heed leaſt he fall into this ſinne: which is by ſo much the more hainous in you, than in an inferiour Miniſter, as it had beene in Saint <hi>Peter</hi> to haue exacted money of <hi>Simon,</hi> for the impoſition of hands, than in <hi>Simon Magus</hi> for offering it. For the ſinnes and offences of the Shepheards are greater than the ſinnes and offences of the Sheepe: Firſt, becauſe they cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe themſelues by ſimplicitie or pretence of ignorance, as the ſheepe may: ſecondly, becauſe they are placed to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them that goe aſtray; not to lead them amiſſe by ill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: thirdly, becauſe while the ſheepheard wandereth by the ſteepe and dangerous places of ſinne, the whole flocke who are taught to follow the Shepheard, doe fall downe head-long into the gulph of iniquitie. And by this reaſon,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:27798:19"/>
the ſinnes of Gouernours are not onely perſonall, but doe oftentimes engender hereſies in the mindes of the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and inferiour people; euery one thinking that lawfull to bee done, which his Superiour, his Gouernour,<note place="margin">1. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>quiſquis.</hi>
               </note> and his Paſtour doth; which is a kinde of hereſie. And for this cauſe (peraduenture) in the Canon law, <hi>Simonie</hi> is called hereſie; becauſe when the inferiours buy their orders, or their inſtitutions, or their preſentations of their Superiors, whoſe ſteps and examples they thinke they ſhould follow, they are perſwaded they may doo the like when occaſion ſerueth, without any offence, both by the example of their Superiours, as alſo by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of all nations; for as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith <hi>Quae emeris vendere gentium ius est,</hi> It is the law of nations, that a man may ſell what hee hath bought:<note place="margin">De benef. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> Wherefore you that doe ſtand, take heed leaſt you fall, and become Authors of this damnable ſinne, and pernicious hereſie.</p>
            <p>Secondly. You that are my Brethren of the Cleargie, foraſmuch as <hi>conſenſere mores peccatis,</hi> this ſinne is become cuſtomable in this land; <hi>&amp; videtur licitum quia publicum,</hi> and it is thought lawfull becauſe it is ſo common; and there is no <hi>Simonie</hi> wherein you are not one partie, if not both; I will be bolder with you: and yet that my words may car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie more credit, I will vſe S. <hi>Bernards</hi> exhortation;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epist.</hi> 42.</note> 
               <hi>Longè à vobis remouete malum tempori vetus, ſed cupiditati nouum, ſi moniam, &amp;c.</hi> Remooue, remooue farre from you this Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, for age an old ſinne (being the firſt hereſie that ſprang vp in chriſtianitie after the aſcenſion of our Sauiour Chriſt) though freſh and new in dayly practiſe. Remooue I ſay this Simonie, and couetouſneſſe, and ambition the authour of it; for theſe are not ſinnes where-vnto ſpirituall men are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, but theſe are the temptations of meere carnall men. The firſt temptation wherewith the diuell aſſaulted our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt, was for the neceſſarie ſuſtenance of nature by food, when hee ſaid; <hi>Si filius Dei es,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 4.</note> If thou bee the ſonne of God, make theſe ſtones bread: to want neceſſaries to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine nature, bread for the belly, and cloath for the backe, is a great temptation, and may fall vpon a ſpirituall man; and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:27798:20"/>
therefore hee ſaith, <hi>Si filius Dei es,</hi> If thou bee the ſonne of God; as though this temptation might mooue the very ſonne of God: but yet for all that, let not this temptation force you to Simonie,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 11.</note> but after the counſell of the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Stand ſtill in thy ſtate, and trust in the Lord; for it is an eaſie thing for the Lord,</hi> ſubito honeſtare pauperem, <hi>ſuddain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make a poore man an honest man,</hi> as our phraſe is; that is, a rich man, or an honourable man. The ſecond temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation wherewith the diuell aſſaulted our Sauiour, was vain-glorie; wherevnto alſo a ſpirituall man is very ſubiect: for when we haue auoided all ſinnes of omiſſion and commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if it were poſſible to auoide them all, <hi>vincenda ſuperbia restat,</hi> pride and vain-glorie they will aſſault vs; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to this temptation hee alſo ſaith, <hi>Si filius Dei es.</hi> But the third temptation was a groſſe and a carnall temptation, when hee ſhewed him all the riches and kingdomes of the world; that is, the temptation of ambition, and couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the proper and naturall temptations of carnall men: and therefore in the two firſt he ſaid, <hi>Si filius Dei es,</hi> but not in the third; which cannot agree to ſpirituall men, ſuch as you ſhould be in life and profeſſion.</p>
            <p>This third temptation, which is the temptation of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe and ambition, the authors of ſimonie, hath made the Church of <hi>England</hi> as the Temple of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was, <hi>a denne of theeues:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lud. Charond. Leg. antiq. Rom.</note> therefore aboue all things remooue theſe ſinnes from you. It was a law of <hi>Romulus</hi> at the firſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of <hi>Rome, Nequis niſi per portam vrbem ingreditor,</hi> that no man ſhould enter the citie, but by the gates there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and therefore when <hi>Remus</hi> went ouer the wall, hee was ſlaine as an enemie;<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.</note> and our Sauiour made a law at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie foundation of Chriſtianitie, that hee that commeth not in by the doore, <hi>Qui non intrat per oſtium, fur est:</hi> What then is hee but a theefe and a robber, that commeth into the offices and honours of the Church, <hi>per ruinas Eccleſiae, per deſolatas macerias,</hi> by the ruines of the Lordſhips, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes and demaines of the Church, that ſo hee may ſpoyle others, and enrich himſelfe? The Merchant buyeth not his
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:27798:20"/>
wares, but with hope to ſell them at a better price; and can wee hope that any man ſhould buy a Biſhopricke, and not ſell the prebends, the dignities, and benefices belonging to it? No, no, ſaith S. <hi>Bernard, Qui non fideliter introiuit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard. de bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis deferendis.</note> 
               <hi>neque per Chriſtum; quid ni infideliter agat, &amp; contra Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum?</hi> He that hath not faithfully entred, neither by Chriſt; how is it poſſible that hee ſhould not deale vnfaithfully and againſt Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Wherefore, <hi>longè a vobis remouete, &amp;c.</hi> Remooue farre from you that olde euill, old in time, but newe and freſh in dayly practiſe, ſimonie, and ambition and couetouſneſſe, the authors of it;<note place="margin">In vita Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anzeni.</note> and ſay with <hi>Greg. Naizanzen</hi> when hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned his Biſhoprick, <hi>non à Deo excluduntur qui priuantur throno;</hi> not to bee a Biſhop or a Deane, &amp;c. is not to bee ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed from heauen, or from Paradice as <hi>Adam</hi> was; but, to compaſſe an office or dignitie by ſimonie, is as <hi>Leo</hi> ſaid, <hi>accipere ſpiritum mendacii,</hi> to receiue the ſpirit of lying; as S. <hi>Gregorie</hi> writeth, to haue <hi>non ſubſiſtens ſacerdotium,</hi> a Prieſt-hood not ſubſiſting; according to S. <hi>Ambroſe, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematis opprobrio condemnari,</hi> to be held an Anathema; in <hi>Elizeus</hi> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s iudgement, to deſerue a leproſie; in Saint <hi>Peters</hi> ſentence, to merit damnation; and in our Sauiours practiſe, to be whipt and ſcourged out of the Church of God: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Longè à vobis remouete, &amp;c.</hi> Remooue farre from you this euill, old in time, but freſh in practiſe; this ſimonie, and couetouſneſſe and ambition, the authors of it.</p>
            <p>And you that are Gentlemen and patrons of Benefices, thinke not your ſelues free from this ſinne of Simony, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Simon Magus</hi> offered to buy and not ſell the ſpirit of God, or that which was not lawfull to be ſold; for as I ſaid before, it had beene a greater ſinne in Saint <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nic. de Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mang. epist. ad Gerſon.</note> 
               <hi>à Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mone pecunias exigere, quam in Simone offerre,</hi> To require money of <hi>Simon,</hi> than in <hi>Simon</hi> to offer it: heere wee finde that our Sauiour Chriſt caſt out of the Temple, not onely buyers but ſellers alſo, <hi>eiecit vendentes &amp; ementes;</hi> and <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſius</hi> affirmeth that <hi>dantem &amp; accipientem damnatio Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis inuoluit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epist</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 23</note> the ſinne of <hi>Simon Magus</hi> wrappeth vp togither
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:27798:21"/>
both the buyer and the ſeller: and therefore if you be <hi>pares culpa,</hi> equall in fault, you ſhall bee <hi>pares poena,</hi> equall in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment in Gods iuſtice, though you bee vnequall by your Statute law. And ſo S. <hi>Greg.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Anathema danti, anathema accipienti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. q. 1. <hi>quicun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi>
               </note> Curſed be he that buyeth, and curſed bee hee that ſelleth, curſed be he that giueth, and curſed be he that taketh; &amp; he that ſaith Simony in the giuer is hereſie, ſaith that ſimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in the taker is Infidelity, &amp; ſubiect to the puniſhment of Infidelity;<note place="margin">Greg. lib <hi>9.</hi> ep. <hi>53.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auaritia in dandis eccleſiaſticis honoribus infidelita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis perditioni ſubijcitur, etiamſi tenere fidem, quam negligit vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur,</hi> Couetouſneſſe in giuing Eccleſiaſticall preferments is ſubiect to the ſame deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whervnto Infidelity, although it ſeeme to hold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame faith which indeed it regardeth not.</p>
            <p>And no doubt if you were not infected with the ſpice of infidelitie, ſo that you neither beleeue the Scriptures them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, nor the generall and vniuerſall conſent of the moſt holy Fathers, the interpreters of them, in the hainouſneſſe of this ſinne, and the certaintie and grauitie of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it, you would not <hi>touch the hallowed thing,</hi> nor ſell that which is not yours; or that which is worſe, <hi>dare ſanctum canibus,</hi> giue that to your dogs, to your hawkes or your hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, &amp;c. which is the portion allotted to Chriſt and his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters: you would not make that priuate which belongeth to the Church or the Common-wealth, and in that reſpect is conſecrated <hi>pietati &amp; fidei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Policrac. lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> to godlineſſe and faith, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly committed to you vpon truſt; you would not reape that which you haue not ſowen, nor take away that which you haue not giuen; you would not make the monuments of your fore-fathers liberalities, the eternall teſtimonies of your couetouſneſſe; you would not muzzell the mouth of the oxe that treadeth out the corne, either by taking money as a fine for a Benefice, or retaining your Tithes, as an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall rent.<note place="margin">Cic. nat. deor. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> In the times of your anceſtours. <hi>Tanta vtilitas putabatur percipi ex bobus, vt eorum viſceribus veſci ſcelus haberetur;</hi> That regard was had of the oxen that trode out the corne, that to rob them of their portion, was accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſacriledge: they tooke that ſaying of our Sauiour Chriſt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:27798:21"/>
for Goſpell, <hi>Beatius est dare quàm accipere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act, 20.</note> A happier thing to giue vnto them, then to take from them. If the Prieſts of <hi>Moyſes</hi> law were thus reckoned of, why not wee? Wee are not inferiour to them: <hi>Si quod euacuatur per gloriam eſt, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tò magis quod permanet in gloria est;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor, 3.</note> If that which ſhould be aboliſhed were glorious, much more ſhould that which remaineth bee glorious. If the Prieſts in poperie, who ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taught you not, or if they taught you, they taught you but vanities, were thus reckoned of, ſo that they could liue like Princes on S. <hi>Peters</hi> patrimonie; why ſhould wee, which in your conſciences preach vnto you the Goſpell of Chriſt ſincerely, bee ſpoiled and robbed of that very little that is left vnto vs?</p>
            <p>Is it not ſufficient to haue taken from the body of this one ſtate, the ſuperfluous rancke blood of ſo many Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, and by their abuſe irreligious houſes, and to haue abated that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, fulneſſe of blood in our Biſhopricks; and ſo farre to haue opened the vaines of the Prieſts for feare of a Pleuriſie by impropriations, cuſtomes and compoſitions, that for very weakneſſe they are ready to faint in the ſtreets, but you muſt draw out that little life-blood which is left by ſelling your Vicarages, or retaining your Tithes?</p>
            <p>Peraduenture you are of opinion (as I vnderſtand ſome are now adayes) that either there is no Prieſthood in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; or if there be any, wee be all alike Prieſts, becauſe S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, you are a <hi>royall Priesthood, regale ſacerdotium;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.</note> and hereof inferre, that ſeeing Tythes are due to the Prieſt onely, and either there are no Prieſts, or if there be any, wee are all alike Prieſts, either Tythes are not due, or if they bee due, they belong to vs all. But, beloued Chriſtians, that text of S. <hi>Peter</hi> is borrowed out of the 19. of <hi>Exodus,</hi> where God ſpeaketh it of the Iewes, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> doth of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: wherefore if all the Iewes in one reſpect were a Prieſthood, and yet neuertheleſſe had the order of Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood diſtinguiſhed from them; the like may holde in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie, that all may be Prieſts, &amp; yet haue a diſtinct order of Prieſthood and Miniſtery. But by that text you may as well
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:27798:22"/>
prooue your ſelues Kinges as Prieſtes, and challenge vnto you the offices and priuiledges of Princes; but as the vertue of that text will not defend you from Treaſon, or the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of Treaſon whereſoeuer you bee ſubiectes, if euer you challenge the preheminence or priuiledges of Kinges; no more will it defend you from ſacriledge, and the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it, if you challenge the title or priuiledges of the Prieſthood.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Abac, 2.</note>But you ſhall find that <hi>Vae,</hi> that Curſe which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Abacuck</hi> pronounced againſt <hi>Nabuchodonoſor,</hi> who enriched him-ſelfe with the ſpoyles of the Eaſt, <hi>Vae accumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanti non ſua,</hi> Woe vnto him, that heapeth vp thoſe thinges which are not his owne: <hi>Theſauros quos deuorauit euomet</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iob) &amp; de ventre eius extrahet eos Deus,</hi> Hee ſhall caſt vp the treaſures which he hath deuoured, and the Lord ſhall draw them out of his belly: you ſhall finde that this wicked gaine according to the Greeke prouerbe,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> bringeth a rod at his backe; you ſhall finde as it is in <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> that hee <hi>hath tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched a Scorpion,</hi> which no man toucheth without euident danger, by reaſon of the poyſon which he hath in his tayle, which <hi>Galen</hi> ſaith is <hi>mole minimum,</hi> but <hi>facultate maximum;</hi> like the ſin of Simony &amp; Sacriledge, where it is in quantitie ſmall, it is in quality haynous; you ſhall find a more grieuous puniſhment,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> Cito. ex. Ambroſ.</note> as S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> noteth, than the puniſhment of Idolatry, which God putteth downe as very grieuous in the ſecond Commandement, which is to be puniſhed not onely on him-ſelfe, but on his ſeed alſo to the third and fourth ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; whereas <hi>Ieroboams</hi> ſelling of the Prieſthood, turned to ſin vnto his houſe euen to roote it out &amp; deſtroy it from the face of the earth,<note place="margin">3 Reg, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> &amp; the ſin of <hi>Gehezi</hi> who ſinned in Simony and coueteouſnes, was puniſhed with a leproſie vpon himſelf and his ſeed for euer.</p>
            <p>And although you haue liued long in this ſinne, and in flouriſhing ſtate, and not felt the hand of GOD vpon you, ye are not therefore to thinke it no ſinne, or that God cannot or will not puniſh it; for although as the Poet ſaith, <hi>Mars vltor galeam quoque perdidit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iuuen. Sat. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; res Non potuit ſeruare ſuas,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:27798:22"/>
Mars</hi> a falſe and counterfeit Idol might leeſe his helmet &amp;c. and could not help it; yet our GOD by the ſtrength of his arme can doe it, with ſtrange raine or with ſtrange haile, or with terrible tempeſt, or with conſuming fire,<note place="margin">Wiſ, 16.</note> or by ſcarſitie and famine, or with plague and ſicknes &amp;c. for he hath <hi>mille nocendi artes,</hi> a thouſand waies to puniſh you: and as he ſaid to <hi>Senacherib, can put a hooke in your noſtrils and a bridle in your lips,</hi> and make you bring it backe againe the ſame way that you carried it out,<note place="margin">4 Reg, 19.</note> as the Philiſtins did the Arke of God.</p>
            <p>Or doe you not doubt of his power and abilitie to doe it, but of his truth, and becauſe, as you imagine, hee doth not, therefore will not returne this euill on your heades? <hi>Adam</hi> might as well haue argued againſt Gods truth who ſayd, <hi>what day thou ſhalt eat of that apple thou ſhalt ſurely dye,</hi> for he died not that day, but became mortall and was ſure to die, and as I may ſay, fell into a conſumption, which left him not vntill the houre of his death. And I doubt not to affirme that Gods puniſhments are already begun vpon vs, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though as yet they are but <hi>medicinae, non poenae;</hi> medicines, not puniſhments; and God like a good Phiſition giueth vs ſometimes ſharpe potions to recouer our health; that is ſuffereth vs to haue <hi>detrimentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in minori bono,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thom.</hi> 22 <hi>q.</hi> 87. <hi>art.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>vt augeamur in maiori,</hi> loſſe in a leſſer good, that wee may gaine in a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; ſuffereth vs to haue <hi>detrimentum pecuniae, &amp; ſanitatis, propter bonum animae,</hi> loſſe of money and health for the good of our ſoule; yet if theſe medicines wil not cure vs, he wil cut off that part of the Church or Common-wealth, which is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed and incurable, though to the hazard and deſtruction of the whole body.</p>
            <p>And I tell you true, it is no good ſigne or argument of Gods loue to vs, that hee ſuffereth ſuch ſinnes, ſuch capitall ſinnes to raigne amongſt vs without their due puniſhment;<note place="margin">2. Mach, 6.</note> 
               <hi>For thoſe whom he loueth not</hi> (as the Author of the <hi>Machabees</hi> ſaith) <hi>hee forbeareth vntil they come to the fulnes of their ſinne; but it is a token of his goodneſſe and loue</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>to a nation, not to ſuffer ſins long to continue, but ſtraight way to puniſh
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:27798:23"/>
them;</hi> as we finde in the children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> his elect people, who ſuffered more temporall puniſhments for their ſinnes than the moſt Idolatrous nations, whom hee reſerued to a finall deſtruction.</p>
            <p>And therefore triumph not in your ſinnes, nor comfort your ſelues in this impunity; for it is an argument that you are out of Gods fauour, and that when hee ſtriketh hee will ſtrike you home; when his anger is <hi>lenta,</hi> ſlowe, thenit is <hi>magna,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Valer lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> great, <hi>&amp; tarditatem ſupplicij grauitate compenſat,</hi> and requiteth the ſlackneſſe of the puniſhment with the waight thereof. And it is moſt true and very obſeruable that <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> ſaid to the Embaſſadours of the Switzers, That it is a common cuſtome with God to ſuffer thoſe whom hee lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not, but intendeth to puniſh, to enioy peace and reſt, and wealth, and pleaſure, and aboundance for a long time, <hi>Quo grauius ex commutatione rerum doleant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> that the change when it commeth may grieue them the more.</p>
            <p>Wherefore to conclude, ſeeing this buying and ſelling of ſheepe and oxen, which were for ſacrifice, and was a farre leſſe ſinne then our buying and ſelling of ſpirituall things, was ſo odious to our Sauiour Chriſt, that firſt of all other things he reformed that, and that diuers times, and by force and violence, and by miracle; ſeeing by the opinion of the Fathers, interpreters and ſchoolemen this Simonie is a ſinne and an hereſie in Chriſtianitie intollerable; ſeeing it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand with a common-wealth, but thereby one ſtate will eate vp another; learning and the Vniuerſities will bee decayed; the Church bee ſupplied with ignorant paſtours; hoſpitalitie remooued from the ſtate of the Cleargie; and to conclude, it is a ſigne and fore-runner of ſome euill to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue to the common-wealth: giue me leaue I beſeech you ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, worſhipfull, &amp;c. who are called, if not <hi>inplenitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem poteſtatis,</hi> vnto the fulneſſe of power; yet to ſome good meaſure of habilitie and power,<note place="margin">Peter Bleſenſ. Epiſt, <hi>151.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>vt auferantur ſcandala de regno Dei,</hi> To remooue ſcandalls from the kingdome of God, and from this Church, from this kingdome and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; giue mee leaue I ſay, to exhort you, to beſeech
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:27798:23"/>
you, and euen to adiure you, by this example of our Sauiour Chriſt, that you would vſe your beſt endeuours to remooue this euill, to cut off this ſcandall, this Simonie, this buying and ſelling, and reduce this diſorder <hi>ad honeſtatis gloriam,</hi> to the glory of this Church and common-wealth. You ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, &amp;c. according to the power and wiſedome that is giuen you from aboue, may be a meanes to amend it, <hi>non est meae humilitatis dictare vobis, vel ſic, vel ſic faciendum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider. l. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaid to <hi>Eugenius</hi> Biſhop of Rome, it will not ſtand with the meanneſſe of my place and knowledge, to ſay that thus, or thus it may bee done, but no doubt it would greatly bee eaſed, if the rich patrones who are <hi>pares culpa,</hi> nay <hi>ſuperiores,</hi> equall, nay ſuperiour in offending, and ſinne onely through couetouſneſſe, might be <hi>pares poena,</hi> with the poore Prieſt, who is tempted to Simonie by extreame ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie.</p>
            <p>I haue beene ſomewhat earneſt and zealous againſt this ſinne, but maruell not at it,<note place="margin">Gregor.</note> for I haue read that <hi>partem habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit cum Simone qui contra Simoniacos pro officij ſui loco vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menter non exarſerit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>quiſqis.</hi>
               </note> Hee ſhall haue his portion with <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> who according to the place he beareth, is not very earneſt againſt the committers of Simony. All that wee can doe is to ſpeake vnto you out of theſe places, and that will be the leſſe regarded, becauſe we ſhall be thought to ſpeake for our ſelues; but I haue giuen you reaſons why it cannot ſtand with a common-wealth, and proteſt I ſpeake it not ſo much in commiſeration of our owne ſelues, who by our co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe and ambition haue brought this euill vpon vs, and hauing guiltie conſciences haue bluſht to reprooue it, as in compaſſion of our ſucceſſors who ſhall ſuffer for our ſinnes, and liue in an age when the finger of the ſonnes will be heauier on them, then the loynes of the fathers, are now vpon vs; becauſe commonly wicked parents bring forth <hi>progeniem vitioſiorem,</hi> An off ſpring or progeny worſe then themſelues; when if the miniſters ſhall bee liberally bred as we haue beene, <hi>neſcient fodere,</hi> They will haue no skill to digge for their liuings, and if they know themſelues and the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:27798:24"/>
worth and dignities of their calling, <hi>erubeſcent egere,</hi> They will bluſh and be aſhamed to liue in miſery, and yet of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie will be compelled <hi>turpiter mendicare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudge, 17.</note> To go vp and down as the <hi>Leuit</hi> did to find them places to dwel in, and be houſhold <hi>Leuites</hi> to ſome meane <hi>Micha, for a ſute of appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel and meat and drinke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the time is paſt, ſo that I cannot ſtand vppon the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of my text, which is the reaſon why our Sauiour vſeth this chaſtiſement vppon the prophaners of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which containeth matter of very great and neceſſary obſeruation, and offereth a larger diſcourſe then this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; this that hath beene ſpoken is ſufficient to trie maiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries both with my ſtrength and your patience: wherefore becauſe in this one ſpeech I cannot performe that which I firſt intended, as <hi>S. Bernard</hi> ſaid in the like caſe, <hi>facio finem vbi non eſt finis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Serm.</hi> 36.</note> I make an end where there is no ende; and end my Sermon, but end not my text: beſeeching God in the merits of our Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus, who at the feaſt of the Paſſeouer entred into the Temple of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and caſt out the buyers and the ſellers there, to purifie this Church of England, and all the Prelates Miniſters and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of it, from all Simonie, Coueteouſnes, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge and impious merchandizing to giue grace to the Shepheards, which care to feede their flockes, and to the people with all humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to entertaine their Paſtors &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:27798:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
